<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discouerie of sundrie errours and faults daily committed by lande-meaters, ignorant of arithmetike and geometrie, to the damage, and preiudice of many her Maiesties subiects with manifest proofe that none ought to be admitted to that function, but the learned practisioners of those sciences: written dialoguewise, according to a certaine communication had of that matter. By Edward Worsop, Londoner. Euery one that measureth land by laying head to head, or can take a plat by some geometricall instrument, is not to be accounted therfore a sufficient landmeater, except he can also prooue his instruments, and measurings, by true geometricall demonstrations.</title>
            <author>Worsop, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1582</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15724</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25997</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120271</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855470</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855470</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20965</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15724)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20965)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 404:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discouerie of sundrie errours and faults daily committed by lande-meaters, ignorant of arithmetike and geometrie, to the damage, and preiudice of many her Maiesties subiects with manifest proofe that none ought to be admitted to that function, but the learned practisioners of those sciences: written dialoguewise, according to a certaine communication had of that matter. By Edward Worsop, Londoner. Euery one that measureth land by laying head to head, or can take a plat by some geometricall instrument, is not to be accounted therfore a sufficient landmeater, except he can also prooue his instruments, and measurings, by true geometricall demonstrations.</title>
                  <author>Worsop, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[76] p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henrie Middleton for Gregorie Seton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1582.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁴ K² .</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A detection of sundry errours committed in landmeating.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Surveying --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20965:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20965:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOVERIE of ſundrie errours and faults daily committed by Lande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaters, ignorant of Arithmetike and Geometrie, to the damage, and preiudice of many her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ſubiects, with manifeſt proofe that none ought to be admitted to that function, but the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned practiſioners of thoſe Sciences:</p>
            <p>Written Dialoguewiſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to a certaine communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation had of that matter.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Edward Worſop,</hi> Londoner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euery one that meaſureth Land by laying head to head, or can take a plat by ſome Geometricall instrument, is not to be accounted therefore a ſufficient Landmeater, except he can alſo prooue his inſtruments, and meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, by true Geometricall Demonstrations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON, <hi>Printed by Henrie Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleton</hi> for <hi>Gregorie Seton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ANNO 1582.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20965:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20965:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable and his ſingular good Lord, Syr William Cecill, Baron of Burghley, Knight of the moſt noble order of the Garter, Lord high Treaſourer of England, and one of the Lords of her Maiesties moſt Honourable priuie Counſell.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the number of our worthie acts of Parlement (right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; my moſt ſingular good Lord) the ſtatute of land meaſure is of great importance, and equitie. Certaine perſons (wanting ſufficient know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for the executing of that ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute) notwithſtanding intrude them ſelues into that weightie function as ſufficient. Sundry of their falſe rules, and vntrue waies of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring, as alſo ſundry true rules (by ſome of them) falſely apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in this ſmall treatiſe are diſcouered. Mine intention was not in the time of penning thereof, nor long ſince, to publiſh the ſame: but of late vpon great vrging, and perſuaſion of him (at whoſe requeſt I did write this talke) and of certaine other my friends and acquaintances: I yeelded at their requeſts to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication thereof. The neceſſitie, and worthines of the matter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire learned and exquiſite ordering, which I muſt reſigne to be performed hereafter by the learned. By this treatiſe I may bee likened to a broyled founder, whoſe onely charge is to make mixture of mettals, and to roughcaſt them. The filing, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and poliſhing, are done by other artificiall workemen, who goodly ſet out the ſame to the eye according to the riche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the metall. I, a ſimple man among the common people,
<pb facs="tcp:20965:3"/> haue ſet forth this diſcourſe to their behoofe, by the playneſt waies I could deuiſe, and for their eaſieſt vnderſtanding: Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry learned workes of the Mathematicals (for ſuch as vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand or affect learning) are extant in our vulgar tongue: as Euclide, the workes of Doctor Record, of Maſter Leonard Digges, of Maſter Thomas Digges, and of ſome others. But becauſe theſe learned bookes can not bee vnderſtoode of the common ſorte, and that they be as iuels, and riches, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed or wrapped vp from their ſight: I haue thought good by a plaine and popular diſcourſe, to laie open vnto the vnderſtanding of euery reaſonable man, the neceſsities and commodities of thoſe ſingular workes and knowledges, and the great abuſe, inconueniences, and iniuries, the common weale ſuſteineth by crediting and reteyning of ignorant doers, and neglecting of learned and ſkilfull writers, and practiſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. As wiſe and learned men, when they ſpeake vnto a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and vnlearned man: frame their ſpeache to his vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, which in the like cauſe they would vtter otherwiſe if they ſpake to one learned: ſo muſt ſome man to the behoofe of the common weale manifeſt thoſe enormities popularly, that the hurt which ignoraunce bringeth in this weightie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter may vniuerſally bee knowen. I (although farre vnmeete to take ſo weightie a cauſe in hande) haue aduentured for the diſcharge of my conſcience, and my duetie to the common weale: to manifeſt (as I beſt could) certaine great inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences which the common weale daily ſuſteineth by vnlearned practiſioners, humbly ſubmitting my ſelfe where reformation is needeful, to the correction of the learned. And for becauſe it is vniuerſally knowen, that the continuall application of your noble hearte and minde, is to the furtherance of learned know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, of equitie in cauſes, ſuppreſſing of ignoraunce, and to the commoditie of the weale publike (whereof your Honour
<pb facs="tcp:20965:3"/> is a principall piller) and for that your Honour hath been mine eſpeciall good Lord, I doe preſume (as enforced thereto by duetie) to dedicate vnto your Honour this ſmall treatiſe: moſt humbly requiring pardon for ſuch my great boldnes, as alſo that your Honor would vouchſafe to receiue the ſame into your noble patronage.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt humble to command, <hi>EDWARD WORSOP.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:20965:4"/>
            <head>The coppie of a Letter ſent with this <hi>Booke.</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="italic">
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O perfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rme my promiſe, and ſatisfie your requeſt: I haue ſet downe in writing (as neere as I can call to remembrance) the communication had in our iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, touching vntrue meaſuring of land, inſufficient landmeaters, and why they are ſtill permitted. For the further proofe of theſe matters, I haue drawen ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry figures like vnto ſome of thoſe you ſawe in my booke: which proofes the vnlearned in Geometrie may eaſily conceiue. I pray you reſerue this booke for the ſatisfaction of your ſelfe, and your friendes. I would be loath it ſhould come to the hands of learned Mathematicians, for they may iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly reproue ſundry of my demonſtrations, and declarations: becauſe they are not penned as learning, and art require. If they were penned in arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall order, and termes: you could not vnderstand them, becauſe you are ignorant of the Mathematicals. If you wil be inſtructed in Arithmetike, Euclide, Tectonicon, and Pantometria, according to your earneſt prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations: and studie thoſe bookes earneſtly, becauſe they are the beſt wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, extant in our vulgar tongue touching the Mathematicall part of ſurueie: you ſhall then perceiue, what great pleaſure, and commoditie, is receiued from learned, and artificiall writers, ouer that can bee had from them, which in their writings diſcend to the capacitie of the vulgar ſort. Then alſo you will yeelde your ſelfe more beholding vnto me for writing this popular diſcourſe at you requeſt, to the diminiſhing, and aduenturing of mine eſtimation among learned Mathematicians: then nowe while you thinke it artificially done. Although my knowledge in Geometrie is verie ſmall, yet I would not abaſe my ſelfe by penning any demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons popularly: but to pleaſure you, and your friendes, and for that I would many ſhould vnderſtand, the great hurtes the common weale ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaineth by landmeaters ignorant of Geometrie. When you haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb facs="tcp:20965:4"/> knowledge, I hope you will deale with mee as good natured men deale with their nurſes. Good natured men during their liues loue their nurſes, becauſe they receiued their firſt ſuſtenance from them: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though their ſtomakes would loath to ſuck their milke as they did in their infancie. When you ſhall finde your ſelfe learned in Geometrie, and that you can vnderſtand the demonstrations of learned writers: you will repute my writing as cold and thin milk, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of other meates, that are ſtrong and of good nouriſhment. From London the two and twentie of September. 1581.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing Friende Edward Worſop.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer type="illustration">
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device probably of Henry Middleton: McKerrow 215, "Ornament of a lion's face over a shield, two owls, and the initials H. M."</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="advert_for_geometrical_instruments">
            <pb facs="tcp:20965:5"/>
            <head>An aduertiſement to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Cales, compaſſes, and ſundry ſorts of Geomatricall inſtruments in metall, are to be had in the houſe of Humfrey Cole, neere vnto the North dore of Paules, and at the houſe of Iohn Bull at the Exchange gate: in wood, at Iohn Reades in Hoſier Lane, at Iames Lockerſons dwelling neere the Conduite at Dowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, and at Iohn Reynolds at Tower Hill. Euery figure in this Treatiſe is drawen according to ſome Scale, therefore the hauing of ſcales and compaſſes, and applying them to thoſe figures, will make the demonſtrations, and proofes herein very eaſie to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders thereof, though they vnderſtand litle or nothing in Geometrie. I haue thought good to giue aduertiſement hereof, becauſe many that would prouide ſuch things, knowe not where to haue them.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20965:5"/>
            <head>A DETECTION OF SVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry errours, committed in Landmeating.</head>
            <stage>Speakers.</stage>
            <stage>M. Peter. Ihonſon a Clothier. Worſop a Surueyor. M. Watkins. Steuen a Seruingman.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. Peter.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſéemeth to be rich paſtureground, a tenant (in my iudgement) may ſafely giue a marke by yeare, for euerie acre thereof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>I would take a paſture ground with vs, and giue that price for euery acre, meaſured with the perche of xvi. foote, and an halfe, called ſtatute meaſure, and ten ſhillings for euerie acre, if it be meaſured with the perche of xii. foote.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>An acre meaſured by the ſtatute perche, conteyneth (almoſt) twiſe ſo much ground, as an acre meaſured by a perche of xii. foote. If the ſtatute acre be rented at xiii. s. iiii. d, the acre mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the perche of xii. foote, will not come to vii. s. i. d, rate like. You ſhould deceiue your ſelfe ii. s. xi. d. in euery ſuch acre by that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>You are greatly deceiued, for by all reaſon, the acre meaſured with the perche of xii. foote, muſt be almoſt iii. quarters of the ſtatute acre, becauſe xii. foote, are almoſt iii. quarters of xvi. foote, and an halfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>Howe much grounde of ſtatute meaſure, are xi. acres of woodland meaſure, the woodland perche being xviii. foote?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Aboue xiii. acres, &amp; xiiii. perches, to my remembrance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>Your remembrance, or your caſting haue fayled you. You are greatly deceiued in both your reckonings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>I ſhalbe very ſory, if I be deceiued in either of them: for I haue made ſundry ſurueyes where occaſion hath ſerued to
<pb facs="tcp:20965:6"/> reduce ſuch acres as haue bin meaſured by the xviii. foote perche, &amp; the xii. foote perche vnto ſtatute acres. The xviii. foote perche for woodland is vſed in moſt places hereabouts: I haue not ſeene the xii. foot perch vſed in theſe parts: but far from London in ſome Manors, that meaſure is allowed of, and is called in ſome places, tenant right, in other ſome, curt meaſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>I alway thought, and haue ſundry times heard that xi. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres meaſured with the perch of xviii. foote, make xii. ſtatute acres. And this reaſon hath alwaies induced me to thinke it true, becauſe the xviii. foote perche exceedeth the ſtatute perche by halfe a yarde, which is a twelfth part thereof: for the one perche is xii. halfe yards long, and the other but xi. therefore ſeeing the perches differ but a tewlfth part the one from the other, the acres (in mine opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured with thoſe perches, can not make any other difference.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>You do not knowe, or not conſider, that when you talk of the diuerſitie which vnequal perches make in land meaſure, that then you ſpeake of the meaſure of planes and flattes. You think you are in the compariſon of lengthes, when as in déede you are in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matter. Ye muſt vnderſtand that Geometrie treateth of thrée ſundry meaſures. The firſt of lengthes, which is called liniarie mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or the meaſure of lengthes, or lines. By this part, you may know howe farre any place is from the ſtanding of your foote, alſo the diſtance betweene place and place, &amp; howe much higher, or lower any place is, then the leuel of your eye, or foot. The ſecond of length, and bredth, called ſuperficiall meaſure, or the meaſure of planes, or flattes. By this part of Geometrie is meaſured, all maner of land, bord,, glaſſe, pauements, waynſkottings, hangings, and ſuch like. The third of length, breadth, and thicknes, called ſolide, or bodily meaſure. This part ſheweth howe to meaſure all manner of timber, ſtone, veſſels, and ſuch like. M. Peter ſaide truth, that the perche of xviii. foote, and the perche of xvi. foote and an halfe differ in their lengthes, as xii. differ from xi. for the one is xii. halfe yardes long, and the other but xi. But ye muſt vnderſtand, this difference is onely in reſpect of their lengthes, called liniarie meaſure. In lande meaſure (which reſpecteth length and bredth) the difference is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: as I wil make plaine vnto you by an eaſie example. Suppoſe you haue two tables, or bords, the one iiii. foot euery way, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſix. How much is the one longer then the other?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20965:6"/>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>By the one halfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>You ſay truth, and therefore you account the one table to be greater, then the other, iuſt by one halfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>It muſt needes be ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>I pray you howe many foote of wainſcot doth a table conteine, that is iiii. foote euery way?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>xvi.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>It doth ſo, and then by your account the other table of vi. foote euery way, muſt conteine xxiiii. for the halfe of xvi. is viii. which if you put vnto xvi. they both make xxiiii.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>You ſay true.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>I pray you howe much is vi. taken vi. times?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>Six and thirtie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>By your reckoning it ſhould be, but xxiiii.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>We al know, that ſixe times ſixe, is ſixe and thirtie, but how proueth this, ſuch diuerſitie in the acres?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>It ſheweth vnto you at the firſt, that meaſures caſt vp by their breadthes and lengthes, muſt otherwiſe bee conſidered of, then meaſures whoſe lengthes onely are compared together. A table that is iiii. foote broade, and vi. long, conteineth xxiiii. foote of bord, therfore a table that is vi. foot euery way, muſt needs conteine more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Watkins</speaker>
               <p>This ſtandeth ſo by reaſon, that it muſt needes be as you ſay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>I haue in my cloake bag certaine figures drawen in a booke, (which I muſt giue vnto a friend of mine) that will explane this error, and ſundry others, which landmeaſurers (vnlearned in Geometrie) often commit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>I pray you let vs ſee thoſe figures.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVorſop</speaker>
               <p>You ſhall when we come to our Inne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>It will be late ere wee come thither, therefore wee ſhal haue ſmall time then to talke of theſe matters: becauſe men ſcatter when they are lighted. Alſo we muſt part company in the morning. Therefore I pray you let vs ſee them now, which if you vouchſafe, I, in ſome other matter, wil requite your courteſie. It ſtandeth mee vpon to vnderſtand the troth of this matter, by reaſon of a wood ſale, that I, and an other ſhould paſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVorſop</speaker>
               <p>To pleaſure you, I wil preſently ſhewe them. Here is the booke: theſe iii. figures proue that which I haue ſpoken.
<pb facs="tcp:20965:7"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>three grids to prove that multiplying length and width yields area: 4 x 4, 4 x 6, and 6 x 6</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>I ſee in deede that iiii. euery way maketh xvi. and that vi. euerie way maketh ſixe and thirtie. and iiii. broade and vi. long make xxiiii. What meane you by this worde (Scale) which I ſee in ſo many places of your booke?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>The Scale is a meaſure vſed in platting, taken at the will of the plat maker, eyther greater, or leſſe, to ſet foorth the plat meaſured in true proportion, and Symetrie, vpon paper, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuperfice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Watkins</speaker>
               <p>I vnderſtand not this definition.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Here (as ye ſée) are ſundry ſcales, and euerie of them is iuſt fiue inches long.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20965:7"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>compass with three scales each five inches long, each with one of the inches divided into 4, 5, or 10 parts</figDesc>
                  </figure> The firſt, hath one inche diuided into iiii. partes, the ſecond in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fiue, the third into ten, ye may apply theſe inches and diuiſions,
<pb facs="tcp:20965:8"/> to what denomination you liſt. The Geographer applieth them to miles, or furlongs. The Surueyor, to perches, the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentor, to feete, and ſo may any other arts man, in naming any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meaſure greater, or leſſe. Suppoſe I ſhould deſcribe a countrie, that lyeth in ſquare forme, xviii. miles on euery ſide, vpon a peece of paper, that is leſſe then v. inches ſquare. In this caſe, the ſcale of iiii. will beſt ſerue my turne. For one inche being diuided into iiii. partes, doth repreſent the length of iiii. miles, therefore iiii. inches repreſent the length of xvi. miles, and ii. parts of the deuided inche added to them, muſt needes repreſent xviii. miles. But if I ſhould deſcribe a Shire, or Countrey, vpon the like paper, that lyeth thrée and fourtie miles ſquare, in this caſe I muſt be driuen to vſe the ſcale ten: that is to ſay, I muſt take in inches, and iii. parts of the ten, in the inche diuided into ten parts, which repreſent three and fourtie miles. For iiii. inches repreſent fourtie miles, and the three diuiſions taken in the ſaid inch diuided into ten parts, repreſent the three odds miles. The ſelfe ſame ſcales wil ſerue, if you ſhould plat cloſes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the like ſcantling of v. inches, the one being xviii. perches on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide, the other xliii.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>I nowe perceiue what is meant by this worde ſcale. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member I haue ſéene the like lines, and compaſſes ſet inmappes, but I neuer vnderſtood what they meant till nowe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVorſop</speaker>
               <p>The knowledge, howe to apply the compaſſes to the ſcale, is commodious, for thereby when mappes, or carts, are peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, it may be knowen howe farre any one Region, Citie, or place is diſtant from any other, eyther by land, or ſea. Alſo, when a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyor hath deliuered vp his plat, the Lord ſitting in his chayre at home, may iuſtly knowe, how many miles his Manor is in circuite, and the circuit of any particular grounds, and waſts: and how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perches, or furlongs it is, from any one hedge, or corner of hedge, to any other hedge, or corner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>I perceiue alſo what you ment, when you ſaid, ye may apply theſe diuiſions, to what denominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you liſt. As if you would knowe by any cart, or mappe of England, how many miles it is fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Northampton to Sariſburie, then miles are the denomination: but if you would knowe by any platte of lande, howe many perches any ground is ouer, then perch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s are the denomination. And you call the opening and extending the compaſſes vpon the ſcale, the applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the compaſſes to the ſcale.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>You conceiſſe the meaning rightly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>What meane you by theſe ſeuerall words, in true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion,
<pb facs="tcp:20965:8"/> Symetrie, and ſuperfice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVorſop</speaker>
               <p>To ſet forth a plat, in true proportion and Symetrie, are to ſay, to take, and ſet forth any plat in ſuch ſort, that you may readily tel thereby, euerie angle, bought, crooke, and ſtraight line in the thing meaſured, and howe farre any place is diſtant from other. Alſo you may know by your plat the whole circuit, &amp; outboundes of your land, which Geometers call the perimetrie. Superfice is to ſay, the vpper face of any thing, as in meaſuring of lande, paue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, hangings, &amp; ſuch like, we deſire only to know the content of the outward plaine, or vpper face of the thing, not regarding thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, weight, groſſenes or depth: but only the meſure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vpper parts as in groundes: which conſiſt onely of length, and bredth, whether they be flats, or leuels, hils, or valleis. It would be too tedious to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe them at large: therefore I referre you to learned authors for your further inſtructions of their proprieties, and accidentes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>What is meant by this word, Parallel?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVorſop</speaker>
               <p>Parallel lines, are ſuch lines, as (being drawen v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon any plaine, or ſuperfice) are equally diſtant y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. If you draw them of neuer ſo great a length, yet will they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer concur, or meet together. If they incline neuer ſo litle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, they are not parallels, but inclining lines, as you may ſee by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>parallel lines ab and cd; inclining lines ef and gh</figDesc>
                  </figure> examples of theſe lines a. b. &amp;c. d. which are parallels, and the lines e. f. &amp; g. h, which are inclining.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ihon.</speaker>
               <p>Why write you ſuch ſtrange &amp; far fetched words &amp; termes, ſeeing you can write their meanings in plaine engliſh, if you wold?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20965:9"/>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>He for whom I haue written this booke, wil not think them ſtrange, or far fetched, becauſe he giueth himſelf to the ſtudies of Arithmetike &amp; Geometrie, and therfore acquainted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> words and termes of thoſe arts. There is not any doctrine, or ſcience, but hath of neceſſitie his peculiar termes: neyther doeth any learned man in any ſcience, condemne an other learned man, in an other ſcience, for a ſtrange and farre fetching ſpeaker, becauſe hee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth not many of his wordes and termes. Many of the profoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt learned men in the Vniuerſities, vnderſtand not a number of termes, pertaining to the common Lawes, which a young ſtudent of leſſe then a yeres continuance, vnderſtandeth very well. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, a great number of profound learned men in the lawes of the Realme, vnderſtand not a great number of termes, vſed in Philoſophie and Logike, which a young Logician vnderſtandeth very well. The Ciuilian, vnderſtandeth not many termes of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſike, nor the Phyſition many termes appertaining to the Ciuill Lawes. The Greeke termes appertaining to Arithmetike, Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and other Mathematicall ſciences, ſeeme ſtranger vnto al ſortes of men, then the termes of other ſciences, and therefore, of the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant very much derided, who account them more curious then ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie. Yea ſome men that are learned in other ſciences, but igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in the Mathematikes, thinke them termes of hard and darke knowledges, and not greatly neceſſary, becauſe they thinke much vanitie in them. Both theſe ſortes of men, which condemne before they knowe, are in great error. The auncients, and beſt learned writers of Mathematicall ſciences, were Grecians: the Latines, receiuing their knowledge from learned Greeke authors, neuer al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the Greeke termes, but vſed them aſwell in workes of their owne making, as in tranſlations. The Italians, Frenche men, and Germanes, finding them in the Latine, vſed alſo the Greeke terms, as followers of the Latines. Therefore the learned might iudge a great preſumption, and lacke of diſcretion in vs, if we ſhould tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate theſe Greeke termes, into our Engliſhe wordes: ſeeing the learned of other nations, retaine them ſtill, though they can write more compe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diouſly, then we. We are not able to vtter Greek terms compendiouſly, but by circumlocution. I thinke one ſpecial cauſe, why learned writers in the beſt languages, vſe the Greeke termes in all their workes, is, becauſe readers of their bookes ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
<pb facs="tcp:20965:9"/> them, with Greeke, and Latine authours, in whom they ſhall finde the ſelfe ſame termes, whereby the knowledge of theſe ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, is much eaſier attained vnto. For if a man finde one thing in ſundry languages, and diuers waies defined demonſtrated, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, he is very hard of capacitie, if he ſhal not be able to vnderſtand ſome of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ihonſon</speaker>
               <p>I thought verily before you tolde theſe cauſes, that you, and your friend for whom you haue written this booke, had deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed termes much like the deuiſe of Pedlers Frenche, becauſe you would not haue your cunnings in land meaſuring knowen to any but to your ſelues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Steuen</speaker>
               <p>And I would haue thought them, words of coniurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe being once in a place, and halfe a doſſen others beſide my ſelfe, where lay a booke that had many croſſes in it, &amp; a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of like figures, and circles, and as one of our company did reade ſuch ſtrange wordes, one other ſaide: my friend, you were not beſt to reade too farre in that booke, leaſt you fetche one vp, that will aſke what he ſhall doe, and if you can appoint him nothing, neither know howe to laye him downe againe, he will doe much hurt. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was in a Prieſts his houſe, I may ſay to you, it ſo feared ſome fooles of vs, that we were glad when we were out of dores. I neuer heard that the Prieſt was ſuſpected for coniuring, he coulde doe many pretie feates, for he made dials vpon walles, and in gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, he could meaſure land, and tel howe wheeles, and other gins for milnes ſhould be made. He hath told how things ſhould be made and mended, concerning water workes, and milnes, that if the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie had lacked his helpe, a great deale of money would haue beene ſpent in vaine by moſt mens ſayings. I heard him ſay vnto lande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſurers, that they muſt néedes make wrong meaſure, if they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeded by ſuch way as they had caſt their worke, and determined to procéed. One time (as I waited on my maſter when he went to the meaſuring of a meadowe that laye ii. miles from his houſe) there was great talke, and arguing by the way, whether it were poſſible to tel how far one place in view is diſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t from an other: &amp; how much one place is higher then an other, except it were firſt meaſured. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Morgan anſwered that it was poſſible, &amp; very eaſie to be done. Then Maſter Allen aſked him if he could doe it by any of thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments we carried with vs. He anſwered that he could. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon
<pb facs="tcp:20965:10"/> M. Allen ſuddenly ſtaying, ſayd: I pray you tel me how farre it is from the place where I ſtand to yonder oke. I wil, ſayd he, and immediatly he piched one of his inſtrumentes, and looked thorowe a fine knacke, or Iig, and meaſured a good pretie way from him, not towards the marke, but ſidewiſe: and at the corner where his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring ended, he looked againe through his Iig, and caſting a little with his pen, he tolde iuſtly almoſt how many perches it was from his foote to the oke: for he miſſed not a perch in a length that was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue fiue furlonges. When we came to the oke, whoſe height from a certaine knot in a bowgh, downe to the ground was almoſt thrée and fiftie foote, he tolde within two inches the iuſt height by looking through an other Iig. One did clime the trée, and laide one ende of a wier line to the knot, and there helde it, and let the other end fall downe, by which meanes we made trial. We that ſawe how néere he had tolde the length, and height, before they were meaſured, ſayd it was pretely done. M. Allen aſked if any good ſeruice, or commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie to the common weale might enſue by theſe fine ſleightes. Yea ſayde M. Morgan, very much. For except a man can take lengthes and diſtances, he is inſufficient to meaſure lande: becauſe in lande meaſuring, the meaſurer many times through the impedimentes of thickets, waters, myers &amp; ſuch like, muſt be driuen to take lengths, &amp; diſtances. Neither hils, nor dales, for the moſt part can truely be meaſured, except their heightes and depthes be taken. Alſo he that can exactly take them, can giue a very néere geſſe, when he cometh on any ground whether it will co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine his generals army or not. He alſo can tell what quantitie of grounde the enemies campe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpreadeth: and giue a néere geſſe (if he ſée the enemies in battaile raye) what number is of them. Alſo to know how to take lengthes, &amp; heightes, be chiefe pointes in vndermining: namely if the vndermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning begin far from the place that ſhould be blowen vp. The height of towers, ſtéeples, and wales, are knowen hereby, ſo that ſcaling ladders may be made fit: and it may be knowen howe much is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene ſtory and ſtory in any houſe, without meaſuring them. Alſo how many foote high any trée dothbeare timber, and moſt requiſite to batteries, &amp; bowgeings, and to knowe how farre any péece bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth point blank. The degrees of longitude, and latitude, the eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the poles, and the height of the ſunne, thinges in nauiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of greate neceſſitie: namely in long and farre viages, when
<pb facs="tcp:20965:10"/> they would knowe vnto what coaſtes, and countries they are néereſt, are knowen, and founde out by geometricall inſtrumentes prepared for the taking of heightes, lengthes, and diſtances. The chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt péece of arte in the deſcription of countries, is the taking of heightes, lengthes, and diſtances. The knowledge of them are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to many other neceſſarie matters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>Call you theſe pretie feates, and fine ſleightes, and ſuch inſtrumentes, knackes, and Iigges? Mee thinketh hee that can doe theſe thinges, performeth matters of great weight in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale, and ought as much to be accounted of, and aduanced for theſe knowledges, as learned men in other faculties for their knowledges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Steuen</speaker>
               <p>When the lande was parted betwéene my Maiſtres, and her thrée ſiſters, M. Morgane was a whole moneth with my maiſter, and meaſured for him. There were then certaine law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeres, ſurueyors, and countrye meaſurers, and for thrée or foure dayes great controuerſie was among them, and ſuch a ſtur as I neuer ſawe amongſt wiſe men. Some would haue the lande mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured one way, ſome another: ſome brought long poles, ſome lines that had a knot at the ende of euerie perche, ſome lines that were ſodden in roſen and waxe, M. Morgane had a line of wyers. They meaſured the poles, and lines with two foote rulers, &amp; yardes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome differed from other, halfe an inche, which made great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance, for euery man iuſtified his owne ruler. If I durſt to haue aduentured at the firſt, I could I haue gayned twentie nobles by laying on maſter Morgane his doings. There was ſuch luſtie bargaining on all ſides, that crownes, and angelles were but try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling layes. Maiſter Morgane layed little or nothing, but alwayes as he ſayde, ſo it was agreed vpon: he could alwayes giue ſuch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſo well proue his doings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>Then he meaſured for them all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Steuen</speaker>
               <p>Nay, that he did not. The lande was to be deuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to foure partes. The ſiſters and their huſbandes agreed that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them ſhoulde bring their ſurueyours at the time appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: ſo that when any ground was to be meaſured, rented, and valued, it might bee agreed vpon by their generall conſentes.
<pb facs="tcp:20965:11"/> Order was taken that a certaine meade ſhould firſt be meaſured, &amp; that euery meaſurer, ſhould meaſure by himſelfe, and that none of the other meaſurers ſhould be with them: and that euery man when he had done, ſhould deliuer vp his content of acres vnto Maſter Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, who went with them to receiue the ſame, and to ſée that one ſhould not tell another howe much hee made it, becauſe it was thought good to ſee howe they would agree. But when their recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings were compared together, they diſagreed very much. For one made it xxiii. acres, an other xxi. and an halfe, an other xvi. and iii. roodes, and Maſter Morgane made it xvii. and almoſt a roode. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon roſe great contention and wagering, but at laſt all gaue place to Maiſter Morgane his meaſure. He that made it xvi. acres and iii. roodes, found that he miſreckoned himſelfe almoſt iiii. acres too litle, and afterwards he ſware by Gods ſoule that he was glad thereof, becauſe by that occaſion his content came néereſt to Maſter Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ihonſon</speaker>
               <p>I maruaile what may be the cauſes of their ſo great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeings, and differences in one, and the ſame ſo ſmall a piece of grounde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>No maruaile, for the common ignorant meaſurers by their generall rule are for the moſt part ſubiect to make groundes greater in quantitie then in troth they are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>I would very faine ſee howe it can be proued, that xi. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres by the xviii. foote perche, make of ſtatute meaſure xiii. acres and xiiii. perches. When I am ſatiſfied in that matter, we wil heare fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of that partition.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Number the ſquare féete, conteined in theſe iii. figures. The figure A. ſheweth the ſquare féet conteined in the ſtatute perch, which are CC. lxxii. and a quarter. The figure B. the ſquare féete in the xviii. foote perche, which are C C C. xxiiii. And the figure C. the ſquare féete, in the xii. foote perche, which are. C. xl. iiii. Your opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are, that a meaſure made with the xviii. foote perche, is greater then a meaſure made by the xii. by the one halfe, becauſe xviii. is xii. and the halfe of xii. But ye ſee it is farre otherwiſe, for C C C. xxiiii. the greateſt ſquare, conteineth C. xliiii. the leſt ſquare, twiſe, and xxxvi. ouer, which is the fourth part of C. xliiii. So that one acre meaſured by the xviii. foote perche, is equall vnto ii. acres, and a roode, meaſured by the perche of xii. foote. Such proportion as the
<pb facs="tcp:20965:11"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>surveyor's diagrams: grids showing the number of square feet in (A) the statute perch (16-1/2 feet); (B) the 18-foot perch; (C) the 12-foot perch</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20965:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſquares of perches haue eche to others: the groundes by them mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured haue alſo. But becauſe you are ignorant of Geometrical pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions, that is to ſay, of Geometrical relations, compariſons, or reſpects, &amp; that the proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſquare of the ſtatute perch, to the ſquares of the other perches, fall ſo vpon the fraction, as I cannot expreſſe them by number to your vnderſtandings: therefore I will ſet aſide arte, and artificiall termes, in this our talke, and frame my ſpeeche as I beſt can to your vnderſtandinges. Yee all knowe that eight ſcore perches make an acre, as eight ſcore pennies make a Marke of money. Whether our coyne bee fine, or baſe, eyght ſcore pennies euer make a Marke: ſo whether the perche bee litle, or greate, eight ſcore perches euer make the acre. When yee talke of ii. vnequall perches of lande, yee muſt not thinke that yee talke of ii. ſuche vnequall poles, or lines, as Surueyors meaſure with, for they are inſtrumentes to laye out the ſides of a perche of lande, and not perches of lande. If a man buye a piece of Dornixe of a yearde broade, to hang a roume withall, and when his hanging is made vppe, hee lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a yarde of ſtuffe to perfourme the ſame: which hee buyeth. In this caſe the ſquare yearde of bought ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uffe, perfourmeth the hanging, and not the yearde where with the ſtuffe was mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured. As a yearde of Dornixe cutte off from the peece, is conteyned within the boundes, and limittes of foure edges, or ſeluages, euery one beeing a iuſt yearde in length: for that quantitie of Dornixe is called a ſquare yearde of Dornixe: ſo is that quantitie of grounde, called a perche of lande, which is conteyned within the limittes of foure perches beeing layde ſquare. And as eyght ſcore pennies, make a Marke of money, ſo eight ſcore ſuch parcels, or pieces of ground, make an acre. Ye haue told that C C C xxiiii. ſquare féet are contained in the perche of eighteene foote, which ſumme eyght ſcore times, maketh fiftie one thouſand eyght hundred and fourtie. For one hundred foot eyght ſcore times make ſixteene thouſand, then <hi rend="strikethrough">two</hi> 
                  <add>3</add> hundred eyght ſcore times, muſt make eight and fourtie thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande. And eight ſcore, foure and twenty times, make iii. thouſande eight hundred and fourtie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>I vnderſtande very well that this is true.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>I haue tried it in multiplying 324 by 160, and finde it to
<pb facs="tcp:20965:12"/> agree that waies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Yee haue tolde alſo that two hundred three ſcore and twelue foote and a quarter, are conteined within the ſtatute perche, which ſumme eight ſcore times, maketh xliii. thouſand, D. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lx. ſqu are féete.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>We haue caſt this among our ſelues, and finde it to bee as you haue ſaide.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVorſop</speaker>
               <p>Take the leſſer ſumme out of the greater, and note howe many remaine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ihonſon</speaker>
               <p>There remaine viii. thouſande, two hundred and foureſcore.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVorſop</speaker>
               <p>Ye ſay trueth, and ye perceiue that the one acre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedeth the other, ſo many ſquare feete of grounde. Can yee tell howe many times C C. lxxii. and a quarter are conteined in eight thouſand C C. lxxx?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>As wee haue caſt, xxx. times, and C xii. foote and an halfe ouer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVorſop</speaker>
               <p>Then yee perceiue that the acre meaſured with the perche of xviii. foot long, is greater then the acre meaſured with the ſtatute perche, by xxx. perches of land and Cxii. foote and an halfe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. How much is thirtie eleuen times?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>C C C. and xxx.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Howe much is C. xii. and an halfe, eleuen times?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>xii C. xxxvii. and an halfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVorſop</speaker>
               <p>Howe many ſtatute perches is that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>Foure ſtatute perches, &amp; an halfe, xii. foot, and a quarter and an halfe of a foote.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVorſop</speaker>
               <p>Thus ye haue found C C C xxxiiii. perches &amp; an halfe, &amp; a few od feet, which is ii. acres, xiiii. perches &amp; an halfe. If you put them to xi. acres, then you haue xiii. acres, and aboue xiiii. perches, according to my former ſaying.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>I pray you let vs trie the diuerſitie, betweene the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute acre, and the acre of xii. foote perche.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVorſop</speaker>
               <p>Ye ſee the xii. foote perche conteineth C xliiii. ſquare ſeete: how much is that ſumme eight ſcore times?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>C xliiii. eight ſcore times is, xxiii. thouſand and xl.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVorſop</speaker>
               <p>How many times is C C lxxii. and a quarter conteined in xxiii. thouſand and xl.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20965:13"/>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>Foure ſcore, and foure times, and an halfe, xxxiiii foote, and ſeuen partes of a foote, the foote beeing diuided into eyght partes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Ye knowe that thoſe lxxx. and iiii. times are ſo many ſtatute perches?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>We doe ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Howe much money is lxxx. and iiii. penies?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>Vii. s.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Yee ſee by your owne reckoning, that if the acre mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the xii. foot perche, did make lxxx. and v. ſtatute perches, as ye ſee it doth not fully, that your rent could bee but vii. s. and a peny, after the rate of xiii. s. iiii. d. for the ſtatute acre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ihonſon</speaker>
               <p>It is moſt true.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Watkins</speaker>
               <p>Theſe reckonings, and profes, are very finely, readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and plainely contriued. Till nowe I neuer heard ground caſt vp to halfe a quarter of a foote, and ſo plainely proued to euery man his vnderſtanding. And yet I haue heard that ſome will not miſſe an inche of ground when they meaſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>It is a ſmall matter for one to caſt vp any meaſure that he hath made within leſſe then an inch, but to meaſure exactly within leſſe then an inche is a greater matter then I euer knew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny would take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him to do. For albeit the art doth exactly teach y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way, yet are we not able (ſuch is our imperfection) truly to execute the ſame. And where you thinke that this account hath beene finely, and readily caſt vp: you much miſtake it: for it hath beene very groſſely done. The fiue waies are done by Arithmetike. I will by Arithmetike doe more in a line, then thus in a leafe: and in the ſpace of ii. minutes, which this waies can ſkantly be done in halfe an houre. He that is a good auditor will quickely caſt ſuch a recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with his counters. But becauſe neither time nor place would permit me to vſe any of thoſe meanes, I was forced to proue this in ſuch ſort, as euery of yee might beſt vnderſtand me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Watkins</speaker>
               <p>I thinke I vnderſtande what you meane by theſe wordes, ſquare feete, ſquare perches, but yet make further explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them I pray you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>That figure is called a ſquare, which hath all his iiii. angles right angles. Euery plaine, or ſuperfice bounded with iiii. ſides, hath iiii. angles, or corners, as yee may perceiue by theſe fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures,
<pb facs="tcp:20965:13"/> 
                  <hi>A. B. C. D.</hi> You may try by the ſcale of ten that euery ſide of
<figure>
                     <figDesc>diagrams comparing squares (A) and (C) with parallelograms (B) and (D), where the sides of (A) are the same length as the sides of (B) but the areas are different, and likewise for (C) and (D)</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20965:14"/> the figures <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>B.</hi> are xx. in length, and euery line is a ſtreight line: and yet the one figure is greater then the other. The figure <hi>A.</hi> is the greater, becauſe it is a ſquare figure: and the figure B. is much leſſe then the figure <hi>A.</hi> becauſe it lyeth not in ſquare forme. Like wiſe the figure <hi>C.</hi> is a long ſquare, and therefore much greater then the figure <hi>D.</hi> which lyeth not ſquare, and yet the ſides of the one are equall to the ſides of the other. Three kindes of angles are to bee conſidered of, by landmeaters: namely the right angle, the obtuſe angle, and the ſharpe angle. It can not be ſaide that any figure, or cloſe lyeth ſquare, except his corners be founde right angles. Who ſo is ignorant of certaine peculiar properties, and conditions apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to theſe iii. kindes of angles, can not truely meaſure lande. It is not ynough for a meaſurer to knowe the ſides of groundes, by laying his pole, or line, but he muſt knowe moreouer the contentes of the corners: for the ſquare lying, narrownes, or broad opening of the corners in cloſes, make the contents diuers, although the ſides be found equall by meaſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Watkins</speaker>
               <p>Is he that knoweth the particular properties of thoſe iii. kindes of angles, to be accounted a ſufficient meaſurer?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>No more then hee is to bee accounted a ſufficient Gramarian, that knoweth but iii. rules appertaining to the firſt part of ſpeeche.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>Notwithſtanding your ſayings, I like beſt the old ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of meaſuring, by laying head to head, and ſide to ſide, taking their halfes, and that ways to caſt vp the contents.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>That way is not true, but where the corners of the cloſe be right angles, and the hedges ſtreight. You ſhall not finde one cloſe amongeſt an hundreth to lie in that ſorte. The meaſurers eye, is not able to iudge exactely whether groundes ly ſquare (though he haue great experience and good arte) if hee haue not ſome Geometricall inſtrument to direct him. If a grounde of foure ſides, haue not at leaſt two right angles, it may not be caſt vp by laying head to head, for that kinde of caſting will produce a falſe content. Tell mee I pray you, howe many acres a cloſe of foure ſides conteineth, if euerie ſide be iuſt xl. perches in length?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>Fourtie times, fourtie pence, is xx. nobles, and xx. no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, is ten acres.
<pb facs="tcp:20965:14"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagrams comparing square A and rectangle C with parallelograms B and D, where the sides of A are the same length as the sides of B but the areas are different, and likewise for C and D</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20965:15"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>square A, each side measuring 40 units</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>This is a true content if the cloſe lye in ſuch faſhion, as the figure <hi>A</hi> repreſenteth: hauing all his ſides ſtreight, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles right. But if it lye in faſhion like to the figure <hi>B,</hi> then it is but eyght acres. The cauſe of this diuerſitie is, the difference of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles. By iudgement of your eye, you may perceiue, that the cloſe <hi>A,</hi> is greater then the cloſe <hi>B.</hi> All the ſides of both the cloſes, or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, are equall in length, and euery of them lyeth ſtreight. By the figure <hi>a. b. c. d. e. f. g. h.</hi> you may ſee the proofe of this diuerſitie. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſide of the figure <hi>a. b. e. f.</hi> is xl. perches, as you may trie by the ſcale x: and becauſe his angles be right angles, therefore his content
<pb facs="tcp:20965:15"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>parallelogram B, each side measuring 40 units</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20965:16"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of parallelogram B superimposed on square A (from the figures on the previous two pages) to demonstrate the difference in area</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20965:16"/> is iuſt ten acres. The figure <hi>h. d. e. f.</hi> hath alſo euery of his iiii. ſides xl. perches, and yet a cloſe lying in forme lyke to that figure, is but 8. acres. The figure <hi>a. b. c. g.</hi> is parcel of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> figure <hi>a. b. e. f.</hi> which figure <hi>a. b. c. g.</hi> is xl. perches one way, &amp; viii. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other. Fourty pence. 8. times, is ii. acres: which ii. acres, being taken from x. acres, there remaine viii. acres: which are included in the figure <hi>g. c. e. f.</hi> And ye may eaſily perceiue, that the figure <hi>h. d. e. f.</hi> is equal to the figure <hi>g. c. e. f.</hi> for the triangle <hi>c. d. e.</hi> is equall to the triangle <hi>g. h. f.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>If the triangles. <hi>g. h. f. &amp;c. d. e.</hi> be equall, then your mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is, to put vnto the figure <hi>h. c. e. f.</hi> the figure <hi>g. h. f.</hi> in ſtéede of the figure <hi>c. d. e.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>You conceaue it right. For ſuppoſe I would cut of a péece of ground, from a cloſe, or ortyeard, as here the péece of ground <hi>c. d. e.</hi> is cut of from the cloſe <hi>h. d. e. f.</hi> and on the other ſide, namely on the ſide. <hi>f. h.</hi> I would take in another péece for it, in like faſhion, and bignes, as the péece cut of, was, becauſe I would haue the grounde lye in ſquare forme, for the pleaſure of myne eye: your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon giues you, that there is no difference in reſpect of quantitie of ground, betweene the firſt cloſe, and the laſt, becauſe ſo much is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in on one ſide, as was taken away from the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>If the ground taken from the one ſide, and the ground ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the other ſide, be truly meaſured, it muſt néedes be as you ſay: but how can you proue that theſe two triangles <hi>c. d. e.</hi> and <hi>g. h. f.</hi> be equall?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVorſop</speaker>
               <p>The equalitie of theſe two triangles is proued by the fourth propoſition of the firſt booke of Enclide his elementes. But becauſe you vnderſtand not geometricall demonſtrations, I wil not proue it vnto you, as the art requireth, but by a groſſe, and vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned way, for you ſhall ſo beſt conceaue the proofe. Ye may try by the ſcale, and compaſſes, that the ſide <hi>c. d.</hi> is equall to the ſide <hi>g. h.</hi> and the ſide <hi>d. e.</hi> to the ſide <hi>h. f.</hi> and the ſide <hi>e. c.</hi> to the ſide <hi>f. g.</hi> Then lay a white paper vnder the triangle <hi>c. d. e.</hi> and with a pin, or needle, let that paper be pricked in the corners <hi>c. d. e.</hi> &amp; laying your ruler to thoſe prickes, drawe finely thrée ſtreight lines, and they wil include a triangular ſuperfice equal to the figure <hi>c. d. e.</hi> then with a knife, or ſiſers, cut out the triangle drawen vpon the white paper, and lay it vpon the triangle <hi>g. h. f.</hi> and ye ſhal find, the one paper, iuſt as big as the other, without more or leſſe. If the papers be equall in bignes,
<pb facs="tcp:20965:17"/> then your reaſons muſt néedes giue you, that the figures <hi>h. d. e. f.</hi> &amp; <hi>g. c. e. f.</hi> are equall. The ſelfe ſame troth that is in the meaſure of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, is alſo in the meaſure of ground: one reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſerueth forboth. Thus ye ſee, that the figure <hi>h. d. e. f.</hi> is equall to the figure <hi>g. c. e. f.</hi> &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore much leſſe then the figure <hi>a. b. e. f.</hi> And yet the ſides of the figures <hi>h. d. e. f.</hi> are equall in length, to the ſides of the figure <hi>a. b. e. f.</hi> and the hedges of the one, are as ſtreight, as the hedges of the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>If land may not be meaſured by laying head to head, how ſhould it then be meaſured?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVorſop</speaker>
               <p>I am no more able to inſtruct you by one dayes talke, how to meaſure lande: then a learned Phyſition, is able to make you a good phyſition in the ſpace of a wéeke. There is not any that can meaſure land as it ought to be, except he firſt be wel inſtructed, ſtudied, and exerciſed in the ſciences of Geometrie and Arithmetike. He that taketh vpon him to be a lande meater, and is ignorante in theſe ſciences, is no other wiſe to be accepted for a good land meater, (although by happe he meaſure ſome faſhioned groundes truely) then he for a good phyſition y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cureth ſome certaine diſeaſe by chance. I ſhowe not theſe figures, and proofes of errors, that I thinke there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, ye may be made good land meaters vpon a ſudden: but that yee may perceaue, that your vnlearned meaſurers, which you alowe of, and ſuppoſe to doe well, doe vtterly abuſe you, in deliuering vp falſe contentes. There be thrée erronious wayes in great vſe, among vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned lande meaters. One is, to lay head, to head, another, to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure a grounde rounde about, and to caſt the meaſure of the whole circuit, into foure partes, or ſides: and then to caſt it vp, as though it lay ſquare. Many vſe this way in meaſuring of coppies, woods, and buſhie groundes, when they can not ſée how the hedges ly: but howe vntrue that kinde of meaſuring is, you may perceaue by the ſquare figure. <hi>a. b. c. d.</hi> which is much bigger, then the figure inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded within it, and yet the hedges of the included figure, are longer then the hedges of the ſaide ſquare figure <hi>a. b. c. d.</hi> If you meaſure the crooked lines with fine thréedes, you ſhall finde them longer then the ſtreight lines, as the crooked line <hi>a. b.</hi> is longer then the ſtreight line <hi>a. b.</hi> by the length of the line <hi>b. e.</hi> In like ſorte, you may trye the reſt. Thus ye ſée, whether they lay head, to head, or caſt the whole cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit into foure partes: yet either way they make the leſſer grounde, containe more, then the greater. For thoſe crooked hedges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing caſt vp as though they lay ſtreight, will yeelde a farre greater
<pb facs="tcp:20965:17"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of an irregular piece of land shown within square ABCD to demonstrate that crooked lines cannot be used to calculate area in the same way as straight lines</figDesc>
                  </figure> quantitie of grounde, then the ſquare cloſe <hi>a. b. c. d.</hi> doth: and yet the ſquare is greater, for the cloſe with crooked hedges, is included within it. The third way is, they will lay out a ſquare (here repreſented by the pricked lines, which in deeed is not a ſquare) and afterwards they will make allowance, for all the nookes, and corners. This were a good way, if they could lay out a ſquare tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and alſo truely caſt vp the corners. But ſeeing the learned in Geometrie, can not lay a ſquare truly, but by the help of ſome geometrical inſtrument: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (being ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t how to vſe ſuch an inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) can much leſſe do it. I dare lay w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any of thoſe good felows, xx. to one: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they cannot lay out a piece of grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly ſquare, only by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eie: &amp; other help, I neuer ſaw any of them vſe. They alſo cannot meaſure the nooks and corners truly: becauſe they know not howe to caſt vp triangular ſuperfices, by ſuch rule as their fourme requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth.
<pb facs="tcp:20965:18"/> There be ſundrie kindes of triangles, as well of right lines, as of ſpherall, ſpirall, and mixt, to euery of which appertaine pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar rules, to the attaining of their contentes. In woods, rough grounds, and marſhes couered with waters, they, which haue art, cannot for the moſt part lay out ſquares, but be driuen to meaſure, and to take their angles on the outſides, or vpon the bankes, or wals. If arts men can not laie out ſquares in ſuch groundes, the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant can much leſſe doe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Watkins</speaker>
               <p>It ſeemeth vnto mee, by that you haue ſhewed, and proued, that if all the hedges of a piece of grounde be caſt into one ſumme, and diuided into foure equall parts, if then thoſe iiii. hedges be laide ſquare, that ſuch a cloſe, would conteine more grounde, then if it were laide in any other faſhion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>You muſt vnderſtand that this is onely meant of clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of foure ſtreight ſides. I can lay cloſes in diuers formes, whoſe hedges ſhall be ſtreight, and but viii. ſcore perches about, and euerie of them ſhal conteine aboue x. acres, and differ, one from another, in their contents.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>I neuer heard in all my life, that more grounde then ten acres, could be conteined within the compaſſe of viii. ſcore perches. Howe much grounde can you laie within that compaſſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Twelue acres and almoſt three quarters of an acre: it ſhall not lack iiii. perches thereof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>In what faſhion, muſt ſuch a peece of ground lie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>In a perfect round, like vnto this round figure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>In our Countrie we meaſure ſuch a piece of grounde round about, and then caſt it into iiii. ſides, and we thinke it truely caſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wor.</speaker>
               <p>You may perceiue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to be erronious by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> circle and pricked ſquare <hi>a. b. c. d.</hi> which giueth you 8. ſcore perches in ſquare, &amp; alſo viii. ſcore perches in rounde. You ſhall finde by the ſcale ten, that euery ſide of the ſquare is iiii. inches, that is to ſay xl. perches, therefore al the iiii. ſides are xvi. inches, which make viii. ſcore perches. Alſo if you meaſure the circle, with a fine thred of xvi. inches long, from the ſtreike in the toppe, rounde about, you ſhall finde the ſame alſo to bee iuſt xvi inches about, euen as the circuite of the ſquare <hi>a. b. c. d.</hi> is. Your eye giueth you, that there is much more paper included within the circle, then within the ſquare, and yet no more perches are in the circuite of the one, then in the circuite of the other.
<pb facs="tcp:20965:18"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of a circle</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>I wil not ride any further, til I haue tried this, for I haue a ſilk thred in my bag. Firſt I wil meaſure the iiii. ſides of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſquare, &amp; cut of the thred at that length. Now I wil meaſure round about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> circle, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtrike in the top. I do aſſure ye they agree to an heires breadth. It is very euident to the eye, that much more paper is con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teined within the circle, then within the ſquare: therefore common ſenſe giueth, that if grounds be incloſed with hedges of like lengths, and faſhions, that more ground muſt be conteined within the round
<pb facs="tcp:20965:19"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of square ABCD superimposed on a circle</figDesc>
                  </figure> hedge, then within the ſquare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>I neuer (in all the daies of my life) could haue deuiſed ſuch a proofe as this, my head is ſo groſſe. I maruaile much how you can lay viii. ſcore perches in a rounde, without more or leſſe. I take it to be a great piece of cunning. Can you doe the like vpon land, as you haue done vpon paper?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20965:19"/>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>I can lay out grounds in any faſhion, as wel vpon land, as vpon paper: but more time muſt be had, to the doing of the one, then to the doing of the other. Howe to tranſforme figures, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their ſides, or contents, to any other faſhion, or kinde of fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, ought (of neceſſitie) to be knowen vnto landmeaters. I finde ii. ſorts of people of great contrarietie in their opinions, concerning the attaining vnto the knowledge of land meaſure. The one thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it but a ſleight, and learned by and by: the other diſpaireth of his vnderſtanding, thinking his ſenſes ouer dull, and groſſe, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the knowledge thereof. Both theſe ſortes of people, are in wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g conceits. He that thinketh it but a ſleight, is of ſuch courage, that he will (according to the common ſaying) leape ouer the ſtyle, before he come néere it. For ſaith he, If I might be but one weeke in the company of a cunning meaſurer, and haue but a litle inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from him: I could learne all his cunning in that ſpace. So ſclender a knowledge is land meaſure in his ſilly conceit. If this iolly fellowe knowe howe to take a plat by any one inſtrument, and caſt vp the ſame, by Multiplication, and Diuiſion, in whole numbers, taught in the vulgar Arithmetike, he thinketh himſelfe to haue cunning ſufficient. He will neuer trouble his head, with the vulgar fractions appertaining to thoſe numbers, for they ſerue but vnto the parts of perches. Such a meaſurer may bee likened to one that will take vpon him to be a keeper of accountes, though his knowledge ſerue not further, then to caſt ſuch ſummes onely as bee in poundes: if there be ſhillings and pence, he will neuer trouble him ſelfe with them, nor beate his braines to learne howe to caſt them. Such meaſurers know how to make their plat ioyne, although nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther laſt angle, nor laſt length be correſpondent to their ſcale, and inſtrument. If the ii. laſt lengthes ioyne, eyther by in ward, or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward angle, they thinke their worke very good. I haue knowen ſome (when a plat hath beene well taken) ſo erroniouſly caſt vp the ſame, through falſe rules in caſting the triangles, and ignoraunce of the fall of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perpendicular, that the meaſurer which worketh only by the perche, laying head to head, would haue giuen vp a truer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent then they. The ignorance of the time is ſuch, that to talke by roate of meaſure, with making ſhow of ſome inſtrumêts procureth great credit to ſuch meaſurers. Whoſo cannot prooue his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, his plat, and the caſting vp ther of, by Geometrical demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:20965:20"/> is not otherwiſe to be accounted of for a good land meater, then he for a good Latiniſt, who can onely recite certaine ſentences, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnable to perſe one worde: or he for a good Orator, that is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the parts of an Oration, and the Rhetoricall figures. As one that neuer read in the Bible, and yet wil take vpon him to be a Preacher, or one that neuer read Litleton, will notwithſtanding take vpon him to be a Counſeller in the laws, ought to be accounted inſufficient for thoſe functions: euen ſo ought he to be accounted inſufficient for a land meaſurer, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hath not red Euclides Elements, but is ignorant of his definitions and propoſitions: eſpecially ſuch, as concerne liniarie &amp; ſuperficial meaſures. As Euclide is a greek author, ſo is the name of his Elements greeke, to a great number of ſuch land meaters, as holde their credit, by the ſigne of the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Other tenure they can not pleade, then the ſigne of the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a groſſe, and vnlearned order of platting, which they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained vnto by an imitation and exerciſe, and not by learning and vnderſtanding, why it is ſo done. As in Diuinitie, Lawe, and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſike, none are admitted to be practiſioners, before they be ſo ſtudied in the beſt authors, entreaters of thoſe knowledges, that they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to proue their doings, by good doctrine, ſo ſhould not any be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to land meaſure, except he be ſo ſtudied in Euclide his Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and other good writers of Arithmetike and Geometrie (whereof great plenty are extant in diuers languages) that he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to proue, and demonſtrate his doings by their definitions &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Watkins</speaker>
               <p>What is the cauſe why inſufficient landemeaters bee ſuffered, and that order is vntaken, that none ſhall be permitted to meaſure lande, but ſuch as can ſufficiently doe the ſame: beeing thereunto admitted, by the learned in Arithmetike, and Geometrie, appointed by authoritie for that purpoſe. It ſeemeth vnto me (as I gather by your ſpeaches) that the ignorant winne vnto themſelues greate good opinions, and by ſhowes and brags, cary away the doings from the learned.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>The abuſing and contemning of the Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calles, is the chiefeſt cauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> In the time of Poperie moſte ſingular knowledges were ſhut vp. A Ciceronian, was accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an heretike. They could not abide the opening of learned know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges. They made darkenes, and ignorance, two of their pillers.
<pb facs="tcp:20965:20"/> They fedde the people with ſcumme and droſſe, as well in humane ſciences, as in diuine. For as in ſtead of diuinitie, they brought in ſuperſtition and idolatrie: ſo in ſtead of the pure Mathematicall knowledges, they vſed coniurations, ſorceries, inuocations of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, enchauntments, and other vnlawfull practiſes, vnder the names of Diuinatorie and Iudiciall Aſtrologie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Watkins</speaker>
               <p>Coniurations, ſorceries, inuocations of ſpirites, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntments, witchecraft, and ſuch like are cut off by our ſtatutes, ſo that none vſe them, but fellons, and reprobates. I vnderſtand not what you meane, by Diuinatorie, and Iudiciall Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Diuinatorie, and Iudiciall Aſtrologie (as a learned author ſaith) entreate of the reuolutions of the yeres of the worlde, of natiuities, of queſtions, of elections, of intents and thoughtes: it teacheth moreouer to foretell, to call backe, to auoide, or flie the endes of all things that may happen, and the ſecret diſpoſition of Gods prouidence. An other ſaith, that the practiſers thereof ſay, that they can tell of all things that are not come to paſſe, before they come to paſſe, by the courſe and mouing of the ſtarres. By this they make their Prognoſtications, that tell of raine, and faire weather: ſicknes, and health: warre, and peace: plentie, and dearth: with ſuch like. By which alſo, they caſt natiuities, tell fortunes, pretende to giue knowledge of things that be loſt: and laſt of all, appoynt you daies, and times, good or ill, when to iourney by land, when by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when to marrie, when to buie, and when to ſell. Some of theſe doctrines, and practiſes, are vnlawfull. The Prophet Eſay in his xlvii. Chapter ſaith, Let the heauengaſers, and the beholders of ſtarres, and mooneprophets, come on now, and deliuer thee, yea, &amp; let them ſhowe, when theſe newe things will come vpon thee. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold they ſhall be like ſtraw, which if it be kindled with fire, no man may rid it, for the vehemencie of the flame: and yet it giueth no ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to warme a man by, nor cleare fire to ſit by. Thus are they with whom thou haſt wearied thy ſelfe. By this it appeareth, that heauen gaſers, beholders of ſtarres, and mooneprophets, can not by their prognoſtications foretell the ſecret diſpoſition of Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Therefore they are ill ſuffered to foretell of wars, of plagues, of famines, of vnſeaſonable weathers, to their owne deſtruction, as ſtrawe conſumed with fire, and to the deceiuing of the people, who
<pb facs="tcp:20965:21"/> can receiue no more good by their diuinations, then warmth and light, from the ſynders of burnt ſtrawe. Ieremy ſaith in his tenth Chapter, Ye ſhall not be afrayde for the tokens of heauen, for the Heathen are afraide of ſuch. Yea all the cuſtomes, and lawes of the Gentiles are nothing but vanitie. By theſe words they of the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of faith are taught, not to feare, howſoeuer planets threaten by aſpects. In the eighteenth Chapter of Deuteronomie, among other prohibitions, it is forbidden that there be not any choſer of daies, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Iſraelites: for the choſing of daies is an abhomination be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord. It is one of the ſins, for which God caſt out certaine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſraelites. So abhominable are ſuch elections in the ſight of God. One of the ils which Manaſſes did in the ſight of the Lord, euen after the abhominations of the Heathen, was, that hee maintained tellers of fortunes: and built altars for all the hoſte of of Heauen, and worſhipped all the hoſt of Heauen, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the one and twentie Chapter of the fourth Booke of the Kinges. Therefore, the caſting of natiuities, the tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of fortunes by Palmeſtrie, and by ſuch like waies, are alſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations before the Lord. The Prieſtes of the Gentiles, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ignorant of the true God) deuiſed theſe abhominations. They brought the people in beliefe that certaine ingenious men, and women (after their naturall deathes) were ſtellified. They named certaine ſtarres after the names of ſuch men, and women, and made the people beleeue, that they were Gods, and Goddeſſes, and that they had placed themſelues in the heauens, to behold the earth, and doings of men, and to order men, and humane things, according to their pleaſures, and diſpoſitions, when their turnes of regiment came about. The Caldeans, and Egyptians, hauing obſerued cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine courſes of ſtarres, planets, and conſtellations, which God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them in their firſt creation, ſay, that that planet ſhalbe lord of the aſcendent for that yere, which is in the ſigne aſcendent aboue our horizon, at the houre when the Sunne entreth into the firſt minute of Aries. And that all things that yere are gouerned here on earth, chiefely according to the diſpoſition of that planet. Therfore they cauſed Temples to be erected in the honour of them, which they deuiſed for their gaine, and eſtimation, and for the better plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and ordering of the people. They fained a certaine man called Mars, (who in that age, was the moſt politike, valiant, and fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb facs="tcp:20965:21"/> in martiall affaires) to be the God of battaile after his death, and that he was placed in the heauens to our ſights, in the ſhape of a redde, and fiery ſtarre, according to the nature of fierce warriours: appointed vnto him, for his habitation a large heauenly region. An other called Mercurie (becauſe he had a deepe and readie witte, and was ſingular eloquent while he liued here on earth) after his death they brought the people in beliefe that he is the God of eloquence, &amp; the meſſenger of the gods. Therefore Poets faine, that hee tyed wings to himſelfe, when he went on any meſſage, &amp; painters paint him with wings, as they fondly paint Angels. To him alſo, they appointed an heauenly region. They fained a certaine woman called Ceres, to be the Goddeſſe of corne, becauſe ſhe firſt deuiſed the yo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of oxen, the plough, and that order of tillage. The inuention of the art of whooring, is attributed vnto Venus, who therefore was reckoned in the number of the Goddeſſes, and called the Goddeſſe of loue. For ſhe being vnchaſt, and occupied in al exceſſe of carnal plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, taught the women of Cyprus, to pleaſe men with their bodie for monie. This ſo pleaſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſts &amp; the people, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brighteſt planet (y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſun &amp; moone excepted) in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of her, to the greater celebrating of her honour. Many other men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, they fained to be turned into Gods, and Goddeſſes, as Iupiter, Apollo, Saturn, Iuno, Pallas, and ſuch others, ſome for their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane vertues, and ſome for their vices: aſſigning ſtarres, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, and erecting Temples and Oratories in the honour of them. We reade in the Acts of the Apoſtles of Iupiter his Prieſte, and of the Temple of Diana the great Goddeſſe of the Epheſians. Theſe Caldean, and Egyptian Prieſtes, and fabling Poets, fained ſtars, planets, and conſtellations, to be the chiefe gouernours of men, and humane cauſes by turnes, much like the choſing of ſome kinde of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, one yere in, the next yere out, and within a fewe yeres af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in againe. For one while Mars is Lord of the aſcendent, an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while Iupiter, an other while Saturne, and ſo of others. When Iupiter is Lord, they prognoſticate a proſperous, and happie yere: But when Mars is Lord therof, they prognoſticate chiefly of wars, and deſtructions, namely if Venus be retrograde, that is declining from him. But if ſhe be in coniunction with him, the furie is not onely then qualified, but turned vnto pleaſantnes: and in ſteade of great warres, they prognoſticate great adulteries, inſolences, and
<pb facs="tcp:20965:22"/> vnchaſtities. Thus theſe diuinors behight generally vnto the whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worlde, an vniuerſall ſpending of the yere, according to the diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and vſages of licentious perſons. The vniuerſall people at their appointmentes, muſt ſpend the whole yere, either prouident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and vertuouſly: or diſſolutely, and vitiouſly. If any bee deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to vnderſtand at large the vanities, contrarieties, lyinges, falſehoodes, hereſies, and other abhominations, proceeding from abuſed Iudiciall, and Diuinatorie Aſtrologie, let them read the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Iohannes Picus Mirandula, Cornelius Scepperus, and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius Agrippa againſt ſuch Aſtrologie: And alſo two Engliſh trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, the one intituled, An inuectiue againſt Aſtrologie, the other, An admonition againſt Aſtrologie Iudiciall, and other curioſities. Abuſed Aſtrologie, is a greater hinderer and depreſſor of lawful A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie, and Aſtronomie, and the other ſingular and lawfull ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicall knowledges: then rancke weedes of good corne. We may reade in the firſt Chapter of Geneſis, wherefore God made the Celeſtiall bodies, where it is thus written. And GOD ſaide, Let there bee lightes in the firmament of heauen, that they may deuide the daie and the night, and let them bée for ſignes, and ſeaſons, and for daies, and yeres. And let them bee for lightes in the firmament of heauen, that they may giue light v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon earth: and it was ſo. And GOD made two greate lightes: a greater light to rule the day, and a leſſe light to rule the night, and hee made ſtarres alſo. And God ſet them in the firmament of heauen, to ſhine vppon the earth. And to rule the day and the night, and to make difference betweene the light and the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Here the worde of GOD ſheweth for what cauſes the Sunne, Moone, and ſtarres were made: namely to diuide the day and the night, and to bee for ſignes, for ſeaſons, for daies, for yeres, to giue light vppon earth, to rule the day and the night, and to make a difference betweene light and darkeneſſe. Lawfull Aſtrologie, and Aſtronomie entreate not of the Sunne, Moone, and Starres, nor of their courſes, and aſpectes to further end then theſe. Who ſo goeth further, committeth as great euill, as hee that addeth to the worde of GOD, or maketh the worde of GOD a cloake to couer his wicked diuinings. All ſenſible people perceiue, that theſe lightes, gouerne, and deuide the day and the night, for when the Sunne is aboue our horizon, then is it
<pb facs="tcp:20965:22"/> day with vs: when vnder, then night. They be ſignes vnto vs of Gods great power, maieſtie, and goodnes. By the courſes which GOD hath giuen vnto theſe ſignes, wee knowe the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching, preſent, and declining times of ſpring, Summer, Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, and Winter. Nauigation into farre Countries can not conueniently be without taking the height of the Sunne and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſtarres, whereby men knowe in what parte of the worlde they are, and by the age of the Moone, they knowe when it is full ſea, or lowe water in any hauen, or porte, whereby the ſafeſt times of bringing in their veſſels is knowen vnto them. Theſe and ſundrie other greate commodities, receiue we by theſe ſignes. We ſee alſo that our ſeaſons for plowing, ſowing, ſetting, planting, ſhredding, cutting, felling, reaping, and gathering, are knowen by the courſes and influences of theſe lights, and celeſtiall bodies.</p>
               <p>When the Sunne is in the tropike of Capricorn, then is it with vs winter ſeaſon: when in the Equinoctiall, ſpring time: when in the tropike of Cancer, ſommer. Theſe &amp; al other ſeaſons are know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to ſkilfull Aſtronomers by the courſes of the celeſtial bodies. The knowledge of the day naturall (which is the ſpace of foure and twentie howres) and of the day artificial, which is the time betwene Sunne riſing, and Sunne ſetting, is of great neceſſitie in our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane affaires. In like manner to knowe in what ſpace of time the yere is accompliſhed, is a thing of greate commoditie vnto vs. C C C lxv. daies, vi. houres, and a ſmall portion more of time, make the yere: which Aſtronomers haue found out by obſeruing the courſe of the Sunne through the whole zodiake. If the reuolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and courſes of the celeſtiall bodies, ſhould not yerely be exactly obſerued by Aſtronomers, they could not ſet forth almanakes, and if we had not almanaks, great loſſes, inconueniences, and confuſions in humane affaires would immediately enſue. Philip Melanch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton ſaith in an Epiſtle of his, that it is a greate, and manifeſt profitte to keepe a true, and certaine account of the yere. How great would the confuſion be of preſent buiſines, of contracts, of bargains, of iudgements, &amp; how great diſorders would there be, if there were not a diſtinction of yeeres and moneths? If the numbring of yeares were taken awaye, what greate obſcuritie woulde there bee in Hyſtories? The beginning of the Worlde coulde not bee thought on, neyther the begynninges of
<pb facs="tcp:20965:23"/> religions diſcerned, nor the alterations of kingdomes diſtinguiſhed. It is euident, that the knowledge of theſe things are greatly neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to diuinitie, and to many partes of our life. Wherefore the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, or rather the peruerſenes of many can not ſufficientlie be maruelled at, which reproue this doctrine of the heauenly motions, and deſcription of the yere. The greatnes of the profite, &amp; the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the wiſeſt Princes, and of the beſt learned, who with great labour, ſearche, and diligence, haue ſet the yere in order: ought to moue the ignorant to deteſt the hearing, and vſing, of ſuch doltiſhe and ſcoffing reprofes, as are vſed againſt good artes, ſo excellently ſet out, as it were by diuine inſpiration. The worthieſt princes, magiſtrates, and philoſophers, haue had a great care rightly to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe the yere: that times may be diſcerned, &amp; the memorie of things ſet forth, and conſerued. We muſt needs grant that our firſt fathers the Patriarks and Prophets, who excelled in wiſedome, and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes (as it were by diuine inſpiration enforced) haue obſerued, and ſet forth, the diſtinction of yeres. We reade the Patriarke Abraham taught the Egyptians Aſtronomie, and Geometrie. And godly Iob nameth certaine ſtarres by proper names. Great reaſons, profes, &amp; authorities, as well from Diuinitie, as from Philoſophie, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reaſon, might be brought, howe worthie and needefull the Mathematicall knowledges are. Therefore they are greatly too blame, and much ouerſhoote themſelues, in bewraying their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and ill diſpoſition, which ſcoffe at Mathematicians, calling them fantaſticall, and vaine fellowes. They which haue no vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in Mathematicall arts, when they ſee a fellow with a run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning head, or light braine, eſpecially if he be ſtudious, and giuen to ſolitarines, ſay in way of ſcorning, he hath a mathematicall head. They thinke they ſpeake finely and aptly, but they make themſelues more ridiculous vnto the learned by vſing this newe terme, then the ſimple man, that calleth an arbitrement, a bikerment, and him verie vnrude, whom they would condemne for carterlines. In their imagination, a running or fantaſticall head, and a mathematicall head, are of one ſignification, which is farre otherwiſe. Tullie ſaith, If art, and nature meete in an Orator, the excellencie therof is ſuch as he cannot expreſſe the ſame. In like maner, if a man haue a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicall head, &amp; mathematical art, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> man is to be reputed a moſt excellent and moſt neceſſarie member of the common weale. For
<pb facs="tcp:20965:23"/> moſt certainely ſuch a man can perfourme great, and weightie acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to the benefite of his Prince, and Countrie. Howe vngratefull, I may rather ſay how diſhoneſt, and deſpitefull are they which mock at the makers of Almanakes: terming them fantaſtical, and mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall heads, &amp; keakers on the newe Moone: when as themſelues continually carie an Almanake about them, and ſet one vp in their houſes, as a moſt neceſſarie inſtrument to their priuate affaires. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidences are daily brought vnto lawyers, that the expirations of leaſes, and of preſcriptions, and the continuance of diſcents, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digrees may be knowen. Men thinke a fee well beſtowed vpon their Counſeller, to be truely informed in any of theſe caſes. Aſtronomers haue ſo reduced the yeres of our Lord, and the reignes of Kings, that the expirations of termes, may readily be knowen. Theſe reducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are extant in our vulgar tongue, in three, or foure varieties, and euerie of them of ſmall price. Yet Aſtronomers, are not onely vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſed for their paines taken to pleaſure the common weale, but are called vaine fooles for their labours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>What is the meaning of this word Mathematician, &amp; what ſciences be they which you call mathematical ſciences, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicals?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>He that hath cunning in mathematicall ſciences, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Mathematician. And thoſe learnings, or ſciences, which may plainely be proued by true demonſtration, apparant to ſenſe, are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſciences mathematicall. Philoſophie, Logike, and certaine other worthy doctrines, are not learned by moſt certaine demonſtration, but perceiued by reaſon, and ſtudious ſearche. Moſt men wrongful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceiue, that certaine vnlawfull practiſes attributed to Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie are parts of the Mathematicall ſciences, which chiefely bringeth ſuch great diſcredit, and contempt of Mathematicians, and of the pure, and ſingle mathematicals. Some profeſſing Aſtrologie, impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently vſurpe the name of Mathematicians, as popiſh, and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Prieſts, the names of Diuines. As Papiſts abuſe the worde of God by ioyning Pſalmes, Epiſtles, Goſpels, and other partes of the Scriptures to their ſuperſtitious, and idolatrous abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: ſo haue certaine abuſers of Aſtrologie, intermingled their falſe, and vaine doctrines with mathematicall operations. They make the mathematicals cloakes to couer their wicked doctrines, as Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts doe the Scriptures to couer theirs. Diuines, and other lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:20965:24"/> men (ignorant of Mathematicall ſciences) and in manner all ſenſible men, perceiuing howe directly againſt the worde of God, and howe vtter falſe, their prognoſtications of drowthes, fluddes, warre, peace, ſickneſſe, health, plentie, ſcarcitie, and ſuch like are: and alſo the vntruthes, vanities, and ſuperſtitious curioſities in electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſettings of figures: neglect, and condemne the mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cals in generall, becauſe they thinke theſe vanities proceede from them, which is nothing ſo. It is daily ſeene, that euill diſpoſed perſons conuert and abuſe good things to wicked actions. As good wine to drunkennes, good meates to ſurfetting, a weapon to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and roberies, mariage to debate, monie to vſurie, the lawe to briberie, the word of God to hereſie. Yet wine, meates, weapons, mariage, monie, lawe, and the word of God, may not bee reiected and contemned, becauſe lewde diſpoſed perſons abuſe them. In all ages Arithmetike, Geometrie, and Aſtronomie, haue beene ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted liberall ſciences: and muſt they now be diſdained, and reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, becauſe ſome vſurping the name of Aſtrologers haue abuſed them? It behoueth our Vniuerſitie graduates (who are, or ought to bee ſeene in the Mathematicals) to vpholde as much, as in them is, the ſeuen liberall ſciences. They knowe Plato forbad any to come within his ſchoole that was ignoraunt of Geometrie. Hee called Arithmetike, and Geometrie the two wings with which hee rayſed himſelfe into the heauens. Hee knewe, that hearers ignoraunt of thoſe ſciences, could receiue ſmall profitte by his lectures of Aſtronomie, or of ſundrie partes of Philoſophie, and Logike. I haue heard ſome Maſters of Art ſay (which haue beene but meanely ſtudied in Euclides Elementes) that they ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue vnderſtoode Ariſtotle his meaning in ſundry places, if they had continued ignoraunt of certaine his propoſitions, and demonſtrations. A Doctor in Diuinitie, who was vniuerſally knowen amongeſt our learned men, to bee a ſingular Grecian, and ſchooleman: confeſſed to the like effect, after hee vnderſtoode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by inſtruction the two and thirtie, and ſeuen and fourtie propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the firſt booke. He would oftentimes ſay, that Logike, and Philoſophie, could not rightly, and perfectly bee vnderſtoode, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſome reaſonable vnderſtanding of Arithmetike, and Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, were firſt had. And that thoſe things which are of moſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie
<pb facs="tcp:20965:24"/> to ſchoolemen, would be vnto them as eaſie as the eaſyeſt, if they had any reaſonable vnderſtanding in thoſe ſciences. Plato willeth that children ſhould bee exerciſed in numbers, and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring. If that courſe were taken with them, they ſhould (when they came to yeres of diſcretion) paſſe their affaires more vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, and with a greater facilitie then nowe they doe. Some iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Aſtrologers pleaſe well the fanſies of many, becauſe they will prognoſticate good fortune vnto them. Many Genethliakes (to pleaſe the vaine, and incredulous parentes) behight good fortune to their children. When any at yeres of vnderſtanding, is ſo fonde that he will haue his natiuitie caſt: ſuch Genethliakes will learne by one meanes, or other, the courſe, and ſome ſpeciall chances, of his paſſed life. The declaring of them winneth ſuch credit, that the foretelling of the other part to come is beleeued, and expected. Certaine cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſening mates are diſperſed in many parts of this Realme, called of the people cunning men, or wiſe men. Some others as fooliſhly (though they thinke they ſpeake wiſely &amp; aptly) call them Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers or Mathematicians. Silly maidens, &amp; fooliſh wiues, daily run vnto theſe couſeners, to know how many huſbands, &amp; children they ſhal haue, &amp; howe long their huſbands ſhal liue, &amp; whether they ſhall leaue them rich, or not. Theſe companions will take vpon them, to tell, and direct folkes howe they ſhall get againe into their poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſuch goodes as they make account to bee loſt, or ſtol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from them. Yea, they will appointe vnto hazarders, and theeues, fortunate times, and houres to make their attemptes. They ſay if theeues make their attemptes when certaine Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nettes are in ſuche and ſuche aſpectes: that they ſhall not onely obtaine their purpoſes, but alſo it ſhall neuer bee knowen that they were the robbers. Many of theſe wiſe or cunning men are ſo vnlearned, that they know not any one definition, or principle of Aſtronomie, Aſtrologie, or of any other parte of the mathematicals. They knowe Aſtronomicall characters of Planettes, aſpectes, and certaine conſtellations: and perhaps ſo much of the vulgar Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metike as a quicke witted youth will learne in xiiii. dais. They haue commonly an Ephemeris calculated by ſome learned Aſtrologer which is a neceſſary book for many good purpoſes. The Ephemeris is an almanacke, or regiſter, in which is ſhewed among other things
<pb facs="tcp:20965:25"/> what aſpects the Sunne, Moone, Planets, and conſtellations eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie day in the yere haue eache to others, as the vulgar Almanakes ſhewe where the ſigne is, and the age of the Moone. He that can tel when the Moone changeth, or where the ſigne is, by looking in the common Almanakes, may as well be called an Aſtronomer for that ſmall cunning, as they for telling the aſpects of Planets, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellations onely by looking in the tables of Ephemeridis. They haue alſo certaine Chaldean, Arabian, Aſſyrian, and Egyptian au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, as Haly Abenragell, Mizaldus, Hermes Triſmegiſtus, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bumazar, Erra Pater, Abraham Avenezra, Abables filius Zaed, and ſuch others. Theſe authors preſuming onely vpon their obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations (for they can not proue their iudgements by naturall reaſon, nor by Mathematicall demonſtration) take vppon them to foretell by the conſtitution of the heauens, otherwiſe ſaide by the aſpects of Planets, &amp; conſtellatious: aſwel what ſhal euery yere generally befal in humane cauſes, as to euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> particularly. The ſtrange names of theſe Heathen authours, cauſe the more credit to bee giuen to their blaſphemous doctrines, and fables, according to theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes:</p>
               <lg rend="roman">
                  <l>If one affirme he learnd it of a Iewe:</l>
                  <l>The ſillie people thinke it muſt be true.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>It is not long ſince certaine rogues (pretending to be Iewes, or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians) tooke vpon them to tell all ſortes of people their fortunes by looking in their handes. The people were too ſimple to let ſome rogues holde them by the hands, whiles others of their company cut their purſes, and pickt their pockets. Thoſe roges tolde fortunes as truely, as ſuch Genethliakes can. The forenamed authors, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers their auncient ſectuaries, giue ſuch differing, and contrarious Aſtrologicall iudgements vpon euery particular conſtitution of the heauens, that our Aſtrologians knowe not which of them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, or folowe. The chiefeſt cauſe why our prognoſtications are ſo contrarious, is, for that ſome of our prognoſticators write after the opinions of ſome one of thoſe ancient writers, and ſome of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And they writing different, or contrarie the one to the other, of neceſſitie ſome muſt hit right. Their iudgements are as the blinde man caſteth his ſtaffe, peraduenture hit, but moſt commonly miſſe. Seeing vnlawfull Diuinatorie and Iudiciall Aſtrologie, are ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
<pb facs="tcp:20965:25"/> againſt the worde of God: ſuch ſeducers of the people from ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt truſt, and full depending in, and vpon the deitie: ſuch ſclander, &amp; diſcredite, to the pure, and ſingle mathematical ſciences, to the great hurt of our common weale: becauſe ſuch excellent, and moſt neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full actions as Mathematicians (if they were duely eſteemed) would perfourme to the behouſe of the ſame, are neglected, and left vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done: it is to be wiſhed, and we ought daily to pray, that it would pleaſe God, to ſtirre the Queenes Maieſties heart, and the heartes of her honourable Counſell, to appoint the learned Diuines, and Mathematicians of her Realme, to cull, and ſeparate, theſe ill doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, from the good, and lawfull mathematicall ſciences. The laſt Parlement a worthie ſtatute was enacted, which forbiddeth all diuinations, erecting of figures, and ſuch like practiſes, tending to her Maieſties moſt royall perſon. It were greatly to the honour of God, and benefite of the Realme, if they were cut off altogether. The Mathematicals being greatly applied to ſundry vaine, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly practiſes, and litle thought on, or regarded, to bee applyed to ſuch weightie cauſes in the common weale as moſt requiſitely they ought: may be compared to a ſwéet, healthſom, &amp; plentiful fountain, ſtanding néere a Citie greatly diſtreſſed through the want of ſuch a ſpring, and yet the Citizens rather let it run into ſoule ditches, and marſhes, in which it doth no good, then they wil conueie it into their Citie, to their great pleaſure, and health. We greatly eſteeme ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiall ſtrangers, for their deuiſes; and workemanſhippes: but wee reſpect not the cauſes why their doings be more excellent then ours. The inſtructions, that ſuch artificers, or Mechanitians, receiue from Mathematicians; is the chiefeſt cauſe why they exceede vs. He is called a Mechanitian, that can make certaine Geometricall fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, and doe certaine Mathematicall concluſions, by practiſe and imitation, according to inſtruction from his maſter, or ſome lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man: but regardeth not the demonſtration thereof, which is, the ſpeculation of the art. Some Frenchemen write themſelues the Kings Mathematicians, becauſe they haue office, and ſtipend, from the King to maintaine their charge, and ſtudies. Others write them ſelues publike profeſſor of the Mathematicals of ſuch an Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Alſo euery Citie in Fraunce, Germanie, and Italie, hath one Geometer at the leaſt, who hath office in the ſame, and ſtipend from the chamber thereof. Some great Cities haue three or foure ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:20965:26"/> Geometers at the leaſt. Maſons, Carpenters, Ioyners, Paynters, clockmakers, In ginors, and ſuch others: vnto whoſe faculties moſt needefully appertaine the knowledges of making ſquares, roundes, triangles, and many other figures, with their tranſformations ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to any proportion aſſigned: reſort vnto theſe profeſſors and Geometers, to learne certaine grounds, &amp; chiefe mechanicall rules. Such of them as enter ſo farre into ſpeculation, as that they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Euclids elements, proue moſt excelent men. Few, or none ſuch come into this countrie. Mechanitians wil ſerue our turne, yea we think them moſt ſingular men, we are ſo groſſe, &amp; vnſkilfull in arts. As a man hauing but one dimme eye, is of blinde men thought to bee wel ſighted: ſo moſt of vs thinke Mechanitians greate cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning men. Ignorance as I ſaide, and the abuſes and contemptes, of the Mathematicals, are the chiefe cauſes, why inſufficient land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſers hee ſuffered to carie awaye the doinges by ſhowes, and brags.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Watkins</speaker>
               <p>Diuinatorie, and Iudiciall Aſtrologie, and euery part of them, (as I gather by your talke) ſhould be abrogated as vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVorſop</speaker>
               <p>You gather ouer largely of my talke. I ſpake not againſt lawful Aſtrologie: but againſt ſuch as attribute vnto Aſtrologie, &amp; Aſtronomie, ſundry actions contrary to the word of God. Aſtrologie (not contrary to the worde of God) is a commendable knowledge. Philoſophie prooueth ſundrie influences, proceeding from the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall bodies, to the terreſtriall, (firſt obſerued by Aſtrologers) againſt which, I will not raſhely ſpeake: But referre you rather to lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Melanchton that famous Deuine, who calleth them Epicureos Theologos that impugne the lawfull ſcience of Aſtrologie. Theſe matters are ſo farre aboue common vnderſtanding, that wee will ceaſe to talke any further of them: referring reformation where oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſerueth, to magiſtrates, and tho godly learned. Maſter Iohn Dee in his mathematicall preface, learnedly ſheweth what Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie is. In that preface you ſhall finde, howe ſome ouer reache: that is, vnlawfully attribute more vnto that ſcience, then duely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth thereunto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>You founde faulte with mee of late, for ſaying mine head was ſo groſſe, that I ſhould neuer haue deuiſed ſuch a proofe as you made, when you prooued that a cloſe entrenched within a round
<pb facs="tcp:20965:26"/> ditch of viii. ſcore perches, was greater then a cloſe entrenched with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ditches of the like number of perches, laide ſquare. You ſeeme to diſlike that men ſhould eyther ſhowe their cunning, or confeſſe their ignorance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>I found not fault with you for confeſſing your ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but becauſe you ſhewed your ſelfe diſpaired of conceiuing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery reaſonable creature may conceiue, if he wil ſtudie Arithmetike, and Geometrie. Neither do I find fault with the other ſort for ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch cunning as they haue: but for taking vpon them more then they are able to perfourme: namely in ſo weightie a matter as lande meaſure. Ye muſt not think that theſe compariſons of figures, &amp; theſe proofes are my deuiſes. My learning extends not to adde a deuiſe vnto Geometrie. I haue gotten my ſmal knowledge by inſtruction, &amp; ſtudie of learned authors. Who ſo maketh any mathematical deuiſe ought to prooue the ſame in al parts, by Euclids elements: if he can not ſo do, his deuiſe is but a geſſe, &amp; therefore not to be allowed. But if he can prooue it by mathematicall proofes, then you may eaſily perceiue that the like hath bin heretofore deuiſed, becauſe he findeth rules for al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parts of his deuiſe. As a Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>marian y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is able to proue by the rules of Grammar that his Latine is true, muſt needes grant that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like Latin hath bin ſpoken in times paſſed, becauſe he findeth rules therefore: ſo if a man haue deuiſed any thing in Geometrie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he can proue by the elements of that ſcience, he muſt needes graunt that the like deuiſe hath bin heretofore, or elſe thoſe rules could not be extant. Moſt men when they ſee heights, depths, lengths, or diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances truly taken, ingins deuiſed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with ſmal ſtrength draw vp, &amp; hold things of huge weight: manifeſt proofes why a cloſe lying in ſuch a faſhion, conteineth more ground then if it lay in ſuch a faſhion, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though their circuites be equall: with many ſuch like: haue in great admiration the wit of him that performeth ſuch actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. They think men attaine vnto theſe knowledges onely by their owne deuiſe, and ingeniouſneſſe: and not by mathematicall ſtudies, and practiſes. They referre all to naturall witte, they haue no reſpect to arte, nor thinke thereon. Euerie ſenſible man that will ſtudie Euclydes elementes, and giue himſelfe to practiſe, may with as great eaſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Mathematicals, as any of the other ſciences liberal. The grounds, &amp; reaſons of Mathematicall operations be ſo plain, ſo ſimple &amp; ſo eaſie to be perceaued after ſome reaſonable inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; practiſe:
<pb facs="tcp:20965:27"/> that not any ſenſible man hath iuſt cauſe to diſpaire y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhal not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein thoſe knowledges, for children about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> age of xii. yeres, by thoſe meanes may eaſily learne them, they be ſo plaine. After a man is ſome what entred, he doth greatly maruaile to ſee ſuch weightie ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, proceede from ſuch plaine and ſimple rules. Euerie firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the ſtudie of any of the ſciences liberall is hard. How drie, hard, and vnſauerie ſeeme the rules of Grammar vntil ye come to conſtruction, and proouing by the Grammar rules<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> euerie worde of the ſentence to be in congruence. But when you can prooue the congruence, then great pleaſure is receiued from that, which before ſeemed ſo hard, and vnſauerie? Euen as a man muſt know, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand thoſe drie rules before he can attaine the knowledge of the Latine tongue, ſo muſt he knowe, and vnderſtande, the definitions, and propoſitions in Euclides elements, and howe to applie them to his workings, before he ſhould be allowed a ſufficient practiſioner of the mathematicall part, or charge of Aſtronomie, Perſpectiue, Coſmographie, Geographie, Nauigation, Martiall exploits, ſuruey of lands, menſuration of ſolides, architecture, ingins, drenings or mountings of water, and many other faculties. If in the practiſe of theſe forenamed ſciences, the mathematicall part be defectiue: ſuch practiſe may bee compared to a naturall liuing bodie, that hath ſome principall member or members, as armes, or legs, ſo benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, taken, or ſhrunk vp, that they ſtand not in any ſtead, but hang on like deade things. The mathematicall part is the head, or chiefe part of ſome of theſe ſciences. If the powers of the head bee ſtopped, or taken away, the bodie ſerueth to ſmall purpoſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>I perceiue that Euclides elements is a booke of mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall rules, and that by the knowledge of thoſe rules mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall operations are perfourmed, euen as the Latine tongue is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined by the knowledge of the Grammar rules, or reading by the knowledge of the alphabet, and the other accidentes appropriate to that ſcience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>You ſay truth. The elements of a ſcience are the firſt, chiefe, and principall rules of that ſcience: whereof all the operations of that ſcience take their beginnings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>Are there not other authors that haue written thoſe rules, as learnedly as Euclide, becauſe ſtill you nominate him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20965:27"/>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>There is not any comparable to him. For all his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions are ſo fully, plainely, truely, orderly, and learnedly proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: that all ſingular, and learned writers of the Mathematicals ſince his time, haue beene content to be tried by his elements, ſo excellent an author he is, and ſo plaine, pure, and ſimple is the ſubiect of his matter, that he leaueth not any thing doubtfull, or referreth you to a quere. Theſe be the cauſes why learned Mathematicians, make the proofes of their doings by his propoſitions: and rely vpon him as vpon a moſt ſure foundation. There is not any writer of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane cauſes of whom ſo boldely a man may ſay, <hi>(Ipſe dixit)</hi> as of Euclide, ſo free is he from errours and controlments.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Watkins</speaker>
               <p>In what age liued Euclide? You ſaide hee is a Greeke author. Chiefe officers in martiall affaires, meaſurers of lande, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of ſhips, ingenors, dreyners, mounters of water, and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther arts men, of whoſe faculties (by your ſaying) the part mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall is a principall member, vnderſtand not for the moſt parte the Greeke tongue. Fewe vnderſtande the Greeke tongue but Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie men: would you not haue any chiefe profeſſors of theſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties but graduates?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Euclide was liuing about xl. yeres before the Reigne of Alexander the great as Suydas chronicleth. Plutarch in his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the life of Plato ſaith that Plato went from Athens to Mega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, when he was xxviii. yeres of age to learne Geometrie of Euclide. Some of Socrates his ſcholers gaue themſelues chiefely to the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of morall, and naturall Philoſophie: as Plato, Xenophon, and Antiſthenes. Other ſome to the Mathematicals, as Aeſchines, Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Euclide, and Ariſtippus. I haue ſeene Euclides elementes in the Latine tongue, in ten ſundrie tranſlations at the leaſt. They are alſo extant in Frenche, Italian, Spaniſh, high Almane, &amp; Dutch. But in the Engliſh tongue farre exceeding all other impreſſions, moſt learnedly are they extant. Therefore our profeſſors of facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties may learne and vnderſtand him ſufficiently to diſcharge their functions, although they vnderſtand not the Greeke. Graduates that perfectly vnderſtand the Greeke tongue, and the other ſciences (by which they receiue their degrees) are without doubt fitteſt to be publike readers, and inſtructors of the Mathematicals (although they ſhould teach in the Engliſh tongue) and although the Greeke termes are expounded in the Engliſh tranſlation. They can beſt
<pb facs="tcp:20965:28"/> ſhewe the etymologie, and deriuations of words, and termes, the methode, and other parts of learning.</p>
               <p>Peter Who tranſlated him into our tongue?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Maſter Henrie Billingſly one of her Maieſties c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers for the port of London.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>The tranſlation is made by a verie honeſt Gentleman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Euen from his childehoode I haue heard from others, and noted to my ſelfe, ſuch his great paines taken in ſtudie, his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and ſuch his vertuous inclination, and impreſſions, that my minde alwaies gaue me, ſome notable benefite to his country would proceede from him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>How long hath this Engliſh impreſſion bin extant?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Euer ſince the yere of our Lord God 1570. Great pains was taken at the time of the impreſſion by M. Doctor Whitehead a profound learned man, and M. Iohn Dee, who is accounted of the learned Mathematicians throughout Europe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prince of Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticians of this age: as Cicero named Cratippus y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prince of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers in his age. This M. Dee hath put vnto theſe engliſhed eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, many ſcholies, annotations, corollaries, and expoſitions which giue great light, and facilitie to the vnderſtanding of them. Alſo his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicall preface vnto theſe elements, is a worke of ſuch ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laritie and neceſſitie to all ſtudents of the Mathematicals, that I wiſh them to make it a manuel.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohn.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you let vs ſee ſome figures repreſenting ſtreight hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged cloſes iuſt viii. ſcore perches about, that ſhal conteine more then x. acres. You ſaid you could lay cloſes in diuers faſhions that ſhould conteine more then x. acres, and yet but viii. ſcore perches about We haue ſeene it proued in the rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, now we would ſee the like proofes in ſome with ſtreight hedges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wor.</speaker>
               <p>I wil ſhew you ſome examples, by certaine regular figures. I cal thoſe figures regular, whoſe ſides are equall the one to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, and whoſe angles alſo are equal the one to the other. Euery ſide of the fiue ſided figure <hi>a. b. c. d. e.</hi> is xxxii. perches in length, as ye may try by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcale x. fiue times xxxii. make 8. ſcore. It is manifeſt to your eye that the ſaid figure is greater then the pricked ſquare <hi>f. g. h. i.</hi> Euerie ſide of the ſquare is xl. perches, and therfore as ye haue ſeene by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer proofes, it conteineth x. acres: but this equilater, and equiangle pentagon, or figure of fiue ſides, conteineth eleuen acres, and fiue perches.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20965:28"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of a pentagon superimposed on a square</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20965:29"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of a hexagon superimposed on a square</figDesc>
                  </figure> The figure <hi>k. l. m. n. o. p.</hi> is an equilater, &amp; equiangle hexacon (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay a figure of vi. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual ſides, &amp; of vi. equal angles. Euery ſide thereof is 26. perches, &amp; two third partes of one perche. A cloſe lying in ſuch faſhion, conteineth xi. acres, an halfe, &amp; 8. perches. And yet his 6. ſides caſt together, make but 8. ſcore perches, and ſo many are the ſides of the pricked ſquare. <hi>q. r. ſ. t.</hi> whoſe content is but x. acres.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20965:29"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of an octagon superimposed on a square</figDesc>
                  </figure> The figure <hi>v. y. x. z. a. b. c. d.</hi> is a regular octogon, euery of his ſides are xx. A cloſe lying in ſuch faſhion conteineth xii. acres, &amp; x. perches. And that cloſe alſo is but viii. ſcore perches about, &amp; ſo much is the pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſquare <hi>e. f. g. h.</hi> The moe ſides a regular cloſe hath, the greater is his content. For the moe ſides the neerer he draweth to a circle: and euerie circle conteineth more <hi>area</hi> within him, then anyother figure of many ſtreight ſides can conteine, if their circuits be equal in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20965:30"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of an irregular six-sided close superimposed on a square</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20965:30"/> As all regular figures of moe ſides then iiii. muſt alwaies conteine aboue x. acres, if their perimetrie or circuit be iuſt viii. ſcore perches: ſo if they be irregular, that is to ſay, if their ſides and angles or any of them be vnequall, they may conteine leſſe then x. acres, as this cloſe i. k. l. m. n. o. which is but ix. acres &amp; an halfe, &amp; therfore leſſe then the ſquare p. q. r. ſ. which conteineth x. acres, but much leſſe then the former equilater, and equiangle ſixe ſided figure, whoſe content is xi. acres, an halfe, and viii. perches. The neerer any figure commeth to regularitie, the greater is his content. Ye nowe euidently ſee that land cannot be truely meaſured if the meaſurer be ignorant of Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrie: for if his knowledge extend not further then to lay head to head, and ſide to ſide, or to meaſure the whole circuite, and to caſt the ſame into foure equal parts: or to make croſſe meaſures making the one the head, and the other the ſide, moſt of his contentes will bee falſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Watkins</speaker>
               <p>We ſee euidently that the proofes which you haue made are true, and that common meaſurers make much falſe work: but ſeeing the ſtatute for landmeaſure doth not mention any thing of angles, circles, or other Geometricall figures, but onely of length, and breadth, moſt men thinke that we are to reſpect our ſtatutes, &amp; to follow them: and not to follow the new begun profeſſors of Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrie: as though they were wiſer, and knew better what belongeth to landmeaſure, then the wiſe, learned, and experienced men of the Parlement in thoſe daies. It ſeemeth by the ancient, huge, and ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous buildings, and by the acts for al maner of meaſures, and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that as ſkilful Mathematicians were in thoſe daies, as in theſe. The ſtatute ſaith when an acre of land co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teineth x. perches in length, it ſhal conteine xvi. in bredth. When xx. in length, then viii. in bredth. When xl. in length, then foure in breadth. Therefore if I meaſure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſide, and the head, which are the length, and the breadth, I meaſure according to the ſtatute, and other kinde of meaſure then the ſtatute apointeth the people deſire not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>That ſtatute is wel, and rightly penned, but of many (ignorant of the Mathematicals) it is miſvnderſtoode. Though ye finde not termes of art therein, but vſual words, yet thoſe exact ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments, and reductions of breadths to euerie length in that ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute nominated, could not be done but by a Mathematician. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome of thoſe breadths be vntruly ſet downe, yet they of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:20965:31"/> perceiue the faults to be either in the Printer, or in the corruption of their copies. The hardeſt, and moſt cunningeſt reducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are truly printed: but certaine eaſie reductions are printed falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The varieties of lengthes, and breadths in that ſtatute expreſſed, tend to driue men to learne, and conſider, what the meaſure of an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre of land is. I told ye not long ſince y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> viii. ſcorrſquare perches make an acre. If ye haue a peece of ground, that is xx. perches long, and 8. broad, lying ſquare like to the figure <hi>a. b. c. d.</hi> ſuch an incloſure is an acre of ground, for viii. times xx. is viii. ſcore. But cloſes in faſhion like to the figures <hi>e. f. g. h.</hi> or <hi>r. ſ. t. v.</hi> are but iii. roodes, though euery of the heads <hi>e. h: f. g: r. v.</hi> and ſ. t. be equal in length to the head <hi>a. d.</hi> or <hi>b. c.</hi> and euery of the ſides <hi>e. f: g. h: r. ſ.</hi> and v. t. equall to the ſide <hi>a. b.</hi> or <hi>c. d.</hi> For euerie of thoſe vi. heads are 8. perches broade, &amp; euerie of the vi. ſides xx. perches long, as ye may trie by the ſcale of foure. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward inclination or bending of the ſharpe angle <hi>e. h. g.</hi> abateth two perches in the breadth of the figure <hi>i. k. g. h.</hi> which figure <hi>i. k. g. h.</hi> is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to the figure <hi>a. b. c. d.</hi> and therefore that figure <hi>e. f. g. h.</hi> is equall to ſuch a figure as is vi. perches broad, and xx. long: namely to the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure <hi>m. l. g. h.</hi> which is but iii. roodes. For vi times xx. make vi. ſcore, and vi<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſcore repreſenteth iii. roodes. The line q. o. is the breadth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> figure <hi>e. f. g. h.</hi> and not <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. h.</hi> as the ignorant of Geometrie erroniouſly ſuppoſe. And the line v: x. is the breadth of the figure <hi>r. ſ. t. v.</hi> one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration ſerueth to them both. Breadths muſt bee meaſured ſtreight, and vpright, called of Geometers, perpendicular, or rectan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular meaſure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lines in the figure <hi>a. b. c. d.</hi> are perpendicular lines, for they ſtand vpright vpon the line <hi>c. d.</hi> neyther bending in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward making a ſharpe angle as the line <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. h. doeth with the line h. g. nor falling outward making an obtuſe angle as the line <hi>r. v.</hi> doth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the line <hi>v. t.</hi> The line <hi>n. o.</hi> in the figure <hi>e. f. g. h.</hi> lyeth not vprightlie as lines of breadth ſhould: but ſlopingly, for if it were laide or meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vprightlie, it would reach to the line <hi>i. k.</hi> as ye may try by the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right line <hi>o. p.</hi> which is equale in length to the ſaide ſlope lines. <hi>n. o.</hi> or. <hi>e. h.</hi> The eye of the conningeſt Geometer that is, cannot exactly iudge when he meaſureth lande, vpon what partes of hedges per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular meaſure, that is to ſaye meaſures of breadthes muſt fall, but by the helpe of ſome geometricall inſtrument. Ye may by the example of the three figures whoſe heades are viii. and ſides xx. trye and finde that the like, and as great errors may befall in euery of
<pb facs="tcp:20965:31"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagrams comparing the areas of rectangles and parallelograms</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20965:32"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>square ABCD</figDesc>
                  </figure> the other limitations of breadth, and length in the ſaid ſtatute ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, as in theſe. An acre of ground included in a quadrate) that is to ſay) within iiii. equal right anguled ſides, or bounders: as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſquare <hi>a. b. c. d.</hi> muſt haue euery of thoſe ſides to be in length xii. perches and an halfe, ii. foot, iii inches and an half, and the fiftieth part of an inch. Theſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> iiii ſides added together make<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fifty perches and an halfe, xi. inches, &amp; the twelfth part of an inch and ſomewhat more, as ye may try by the ſcale of foure. That length caſt into a rounde cloſe, like vnto this circle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>e. f. g. h.</hi> and meaſured from Eaſte, to Weaſte, here repreſented by <hi>.e g.</hi> and from ſouth to north repreſented by <hi>.f.h.</hi> (as many erroniouſly vſe to doe) taking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one meaſure for the length the other for the breadth: they ſhal produce by that way of meaſuring one acre, and an halfe, and halfe a rood, which circuite in ſquare forme maketh but one acre. Such a round cloſe by true meaſure is one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, one roode, and three perches. Therfore ſuch a round cloſe by that maner of croſſe meaſure is made one rood and xvii. perches more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ought to be: and by caſting ſuch a round circuit into a ſquare, they
<pb facs="tcp:20965:32"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>circle EFGH superimposed on square</figDesc>
                  </figure> make the land leſſe then they ought, by one roode, and three perches. The words, and meaning therefore of the ſtatute certainely is: that in what faſhion ſoeuer grounds do ly, that iuſt viii. ſcore ſquare per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches muſt alwaies make the acre. We muſt not thinke ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy a ſtat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> for ſo weightie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a matter to be made vppon ſo weake a foundation or conſideration: that the meaning was to alowe of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures ſo greatly diſagreeing eache from other, and ſo greatly ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing from the troth ſometime by exceſſe, and ſometime by want. There can be but one true content of a peece of ground, which cannot allowably be found by any meaſurer, but by ſuch a one as can proue the ſame by the elements of Geometrie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20965:33"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram comparing rectangle and trapezoid</figDesc>
                  </figure> The greater number of meaſurers make their meaſures, by laying head to head, and ſide to ſide, as though all cloſes lay in right angles. By which doing I may compare them to a ſhoemaker that hath two or three hundred paire of ſhoes in his ſhoppe made al vpon one paire of laſts, For ſome feete his ſhoes muſt needs be too large, for others too litle, for ſome by chance they may be fitte. Suppoſe there bee a ſquare cloſe, hauing eyther of his ſides xii. perches long, and eyther of his heads vi. perches broade like to the figure a. b. c. d. Howe much ground doth ſuch a cloſe conteine?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>Sixe, twelue times, is lxxii. that is vi<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> s. If it were viii. perches more, it were halfe an acre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Suppoſe there be an other cloſe, the one ſide w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>reof is xxi. perches long, the other but xii. and eyther of the heade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches broad, lying in faſhion like to the figure e. f. g. h. How much doth ſuch a cloſe conteine?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>Xxi. and xii. added together make xxxiii. The halfe
<pb facs="tcp:20965:33"/> thereof is xvi. perches, and an halfe. Theſe xvi. and an halfe I take for the length, &amp; taking vi. for the breadth, I finde that xvi. d. ob. ſixe times, is viii. s. iii. d. which repreſenteth halfe an acre and xix. perches. If it were but one perche more, it were halfe an acre, and halfe a roode. I ſee that iii. ſides of the one figure are equall to three ſides of the other: and that their difference is onely in one ſide: for the heads <hi>a. c.</hi> and <hi>b. d.</hi> of the one figure are equall to the heads <hi>e. h:</hi> and <hi>f. g:</hi> of the other figure: and the ſide <hi>c. d.</hi> is equal to the ſide <hi>h. g.</hi> but the ſide <hi>e. f.</hi> is longer then the ſide <hi>a. b.</hi> by ix. perches, for the one is xxi. and the other but xii. therefore the longer ſided cloſe conteineth more ground then the ſhorter by half a roode and vii. perches. For if ye take lxxii. perches, the content of the figure <hi>a. b. c. d.</hi> from foure ſcore and xix, the content of the figure <hi>e. f. g. h.</hi> there will remaine xxvii. perches, which is halfe a roode, and vii. perches. Ye ſee before your eyes that the figure <hi>e. f. g. h.</hi> is on the one ſide almoſt as long againe as the figure a. b. c. d. if it were iii. perches longer, it were ful twiſe ſo long as the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVorſop</speaker>
               <p>Meaſurers ignorant of Geometrie deliuer vp ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents. Sundry buyers, par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eners, exchangers, leſſees, and takers of land as ignorant as they, content themſelues with ſuch meaſures. When the blinde leadeth the blinde, they fall both into the ditch. Ye haue great reſpect howe much the cloſe <hi>e. f. g. h.</hi> is longer then the cloſe <hi>a. b. c. d.</hi> but ye reſpect not howe much the ſaide cloſe <hi>a. b. c. d.</hi> is broader then the other. The ſhorter cloſe <hi>a. b. c. d<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> by reaſon of his ſquare lying conteineth vii. perches more then the longer. But for the eaſter proofe I will admit it to be but vi. perches, as may be
<pb facs="tcp:20965:34"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram with trapezoid superimposed on rectangle to demonstrate the calculation of area for each</figDesc>
                  </figure> proued by this figure <hi>a. b. c. d. e. f. g. h. i.</hi> The pricked ſquare <hi>a. b. c. d.</hi> in this figure, is equall to the other figure <hi>a. b. c. d.</hi> And <hi>e. f. c. d.</hi> in this figure is equall to the other figure <hi>e. f. g. h.</hi> And the two triangles <hi>e. g. c.</hi> and <hi>h. f. d.</hi> which are parcel of the figure <hi>e. f. c. d.</hi> are equall the one to the other. The pricked triangle <hi>f. i. d.</hi> is equal to the triangle <hi>h. f. d.</hi> therefore the ſquare <hi>h. f. i. d.</hi> is equall to the two triangles <hi>e. g. c.</hi> and <hi>h. f d.</hi> Therefore alſo the figure <hi>g. f. i. c.</hi> is equall to the figure <hi>e. f. d. c.</hi> The figure <hi>g. f. i. c.</hi> is xvi. perches and an halfe in length, and foure in breadth, which make v. s. vi. d. but the figure <hi>a. b. c. d.</hi> being twelue in length, and ſixe in breadth, commeth to vi. s. therefore the figure <hi>e. f. c d.</hi> is leſſe then the figure <hi>a. b. c. d.</hi> by vi. perches. So that by your way of meaſuring ye make that viii. s. iii. d. which ſhould be but v. s. vi. d. which is all one reckoning as if ye made that three acres, which in troth is but two. For viii. s. iii. d. is equall to v. s. vi. d. and to the halfe thereof which is ii. s. ix. d. Thoſe two ſummes caſt into one, make viii. s. iii. d. You ſaide if the ſide of xxi. perches in length, had beene xxiiii. that then it had beene double to that of xii: and you ſuppoſe that a ground ſo ſided, would be greater then that, whoſe ſide is xxi. wherein you are greatly deceiued. It is impoſſible to include any ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfice or quantitie of ground within a cloſe hauing either of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heads vi. perches, the one ſide xii. and the other xxiiii. For the two heads vi and vi. and the ſide xii. caſt into one ſum, make but xxiiii. Therefore the ſide xxiiii. laide vnto them driueth the other iiii. ſides to a ſtreight line: not ſuffering them to make any angles, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be as it were ii ſtreight hedges the one ſtanding vpon the other, not including any quantitie of ground. Two right lines cannot include a ſuperfice by
<pb facs="tcp:20965:34"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of a trapezoid</figDesc>
                  </figure> the ſixt petition of the firſt of Euclides Elements. The cloſe a. b. c. d. hauing all his angles right, is greater then any other cloſe can bee, if any one ſide of his length be made more then xii. For the obtuſenes or declination of angles diminiſheth quantitie of ground, as ye haue ſeene by the other figures, and more plainely may ſee by this figure m. n. o. p. which hath thrée of his ſides equal to three ſides of the figure a. b. c. d. but the fourth ſide is xxiii. perches and an halfe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20965:35"/>
               <p>Meaſurers ignorant of Geometrie, committe the like errours in meaſuring of triangular, or three cornered cloſes. Moſt men thinke that a three cornered cloſe whoſe ſides are xxx. xl. and lxv. perches, doth containe more ground then an other three cornered cloſe whoſe ſides are but xxx. xl. and l. becauſe the ſide lxv. of the one figure, is longer then the ſide l. of the other figure, by xv. perches. But the longer ſided cloſe, namely the triangle <hi>p. q. r.</hi> is leſſe then the triangle <hi>ſ. t. v.</hi> by one acre, halfe a roode, and three perches. For <hi>ſ. t. v.</hi> the ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſided cloſe, conteyneth three acres, and three roodes, where the longer ſided namely <hi>p. q. r.</hi> conteineth but two acres, and an halfe, &amp; xvii. perches.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Watkins</speaker>
               <p>I am now fully reſolued that they which meaſure with the pole, or line, (if they be ignorant of angles) doe they knowe not what, and that they greatly abuſe them for whom they deale.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>The worlde was merier, before meaſurings were v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed then it hath beene ſince. A tenant in theſe daies muſt pay for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry foote, which is an extreme matter. I knowe ſurueyors that vſe not meaſuring when they make their ſurueies, which faſhion I like beſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>There is greater cauſe of good mirth, and ioye, in theſe daies, then was in thoſe you ſpeake of. We haue the light, and frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Goſpel, ſo that our ſoules may ioy in the true ſaluation. We haue a wiſe, and mercifull Prince, who as God his good inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath all the time of her Reigne preſerued vs from warres, ſpoyles, and heauie taxes. If your meaning bee that ſmalnes of rents, and cheapenes of victuals make the mery worlde: then was that worlde merier when the ſtatute for lande meaſure was firſt made, and duely executed: then it hath beene at any time ſince the neglecting of the ſame. We may finde in our Chronicles, that in thoſe daies a fatte oxe was commonly ſold for a noble, a ſheepe for vi. d. a quarter of wheate for ii. s. Moſt tenants that take land after the common meaſuringe pay for more then they ſhould. Therefore if the tenant had true meaſure, he might liue meryer then he doeth. Seeing moſt Landlords couet to let their grounds to the vttermoſt, and moſt tenants ſeeke to ſell their wares at the hyeſt prices: it is verie requiſite for both ſides, that the land be truly meaſured. True meaſure is not extremitie, but good iuſtice. By the Lawes of our Realme, and by common reaſon, ſuch like equalitie, and troth of
<pb facs="tcp:20965:35"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagrams of triangles PQR and STV, separately and overlaid</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20965:36"/> meaſure in landletting ought to be betwéene Lorde and tenant: as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene buyers and ſellers of cloth, ſilkes, graine, liquors, ſtone, tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, or of any other commodities for which our ſtatutes haue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed ſtanderds, and aſſiſes. I know ſundry honeſt gentlemen pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of ſurueie, that many times omitte meaſuring. Surueie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth vpon three principal parts: that is to ſay the Mathematicall, the Legall, and the Iudiciall. Vnto the Mathematical part belongeth true meaſuring, which is Geometrie: true calculation of the thing meaſured, which is Arithmetike: and true platting, and ſetting forth of the ſame to the eye, in proportion, and ſymetrie, which is Perſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue. To the Legall part belongeth the knowledge of kéeping courts of ſurueie, of the diuerſities of tenures, rents, and ſeruices, likewiſe how to make terrors, rentals, particulars, ſute rols, cuſtomarie rols, &amp; alſo how to engroſſe books, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many other things appertaining to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> part, as may appeare in the ſtatute, called <hi>Extenta Manerij,</hi> but more at large in the treatiſes of M. Fitzharbert, and Valentine Leigh touching ſurueie. The Iudiciall part conſiſteth vpon the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and knowledge of the fertilitie, veſture, ſituation for vent, health ſomeneſſe, commodiouſneſſe, diſcommodiouſnes, and ſuch like of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery kinde of ground, building, and encreaſe, in his owne nature, &amp; kind. Some make apportionation, &amp; valuing a member of this part, other think them more worthie the name of a principal. I ſuppoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be in common to al the iii. parts. It is impoſſible for a ſurueyor to make a true value of lands, except he firſt know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tenure, rents, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; ſeruices to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appertaining in their proper natures, &amp; kinds. He muſt haue great reſpects to the part legall when he valueth. And alſo as great reſpects to qualitie, and quantitie, which are the partes Iudicial, and Mathematical. Qualitie, and quantitie be inſeparable companions, they muſt of neceſſitie be ioyned together in apportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, &amp; valuing. Who can tel, what a cloth, or a peece of veluet is worth if he be ignorant how much they conteine by meaſure? A ſkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful man knoweth by colour, finenes, making, ſtrength, &amp; other points Iudicial what euery yard of them is worth: but he can not value the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, except he alſo know how many yards either of them conteineth. So is it of graine in heape, &amp; of liquors, of which the value of a buſhel, or of a gallon may iudicially be rated, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> value of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole cannot be knowen, til true quantitie, that is, the number of buſhels &amp; gallons be alſo knowen. Some ſurueyors vſe not to meaſure, becauſe they are ignorant of the parts mathematical: but refer the meaſuring to ſuch, as take vpon them the knowledge therof. They ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:20965:36"/> honeſt, in not taking vpon them beyond their ſkil. Many are ſkilfull in the part Legal, and in many points of the part Iudicial, which vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtand litle in the parts Mathematical: and therfore they deale not further then their knowledge extendeth. Sometimes alſo the Lorde deſireth not further information then in the parts Legal, and Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial: becauſe by his euidences, records, and accuſtomed nomination what number of acres euery ground conteineth hee is ſatiſfied tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the quantitie. In caſes of partitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, exchanges, buyings, ſellings of land, woodſales &amp; ſuch like: exact, &amp; true meaſure are moſt requiſite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
               <p>Two gentlemen (both my very friends) are very deſirous to make an excha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge. The one hath CCC. acres lying very néere vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manſion houſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other. Lands of like value (which ly not paſſing 4 miles from thoſe CCC. acres) ſhould be giuen for them. They haue deſired me to find meanes how this exchange may indifferently bee made. In leſſe then ii. daies it would be diſpatched. If I may haue your help, you ſhal haue good chéere, be very welcome to them both, and pleaſed for your paines. We wil al beare you company, and help you the beſt we can.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wor.</speaker>
               <p>When oportunitie on al ſides ſerueth, I wil gladly make an equal exchange for them. If the grounds be ſo great as you ſay they are, it is not poſſible to meaſure, and rate them in ſo ſhort a time. As I haue diuers times meaſured about CCCCC. acres in a day, ſo in ſome other dais, hauing had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like time, &amp; help, and as faire weather, &amp; taking as great or greater labour I could not ouer come xl. The formes &amp; faſhions of grounds are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefe cauſes why meaſures are either long or ſpéedie in doing. Many grounds y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lie long, &amp; narrow, by an indenting, crooking, and winding brook ſide, cannot truly be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, without great labour, &amp; much expence of time. Many ſuch grounds haue I meaſured (the ritchnes wherof hath bin ſuch) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men would haue giuen aboue xx. pounds for the inheritance of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery acre therof. When the weightie buiſineſſes of partitions, excha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, &amp; ſales fal betwéen me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: it behoueth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the meaſurer haue good ſkil, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he vſe great diligence, exactnes, &amp; circumſpection in his meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings. If he ſhold miſdo one acre in xx. in ſuch kind of grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds: it were aboue xx. li. loſſe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one ſide, &amp; an vnlawful gaine to the other: which is a weightie matter to the ſoule, &amp; conſcience of him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> either ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly; or negligently ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eth vp ſuch weightie buiſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſes. It is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for meaſurers ignorant of Geometrie, truely to meaſure ſuch crooked groundes. They can not miſſe ſo litle as one in twentie.
<pb facs="tcp:20965:37"/> Many men (rather then they would wrongfully looſe halfe an acre of their inheritance) would ſpend an hundreth pounds in the lawe for the maintenaunce of their right. Many times through the ignorance of vnſkilfull meaſurers, they looſe ſcores of acres: yea ſometimes in great grounds hundreths. But that which the eye ſeeth not, the heart rueth not. The blinde eate many flies they knowe not of. Many thinke that a Geometer can meaſure lande in ſhorter time, then a common meaſurer that meaſureth onely with the pole. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkilfull, and vnlearned meaſurers (for the moſt part) make more haſt then good ſpéed. The ignorant thinke if a Geometer but once looke through the ſights in his inſtrument, that thereby he knoweth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently howe many acres the grounde conteineth. True Geometri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call meaſure aſketh longer time then onely running ouer a grounde with a perche, or a line. Great cheere, and company keeping, binder much in the time of ſurueying. A good ſurueyor will auoide them. Diligent and exact ſurueying ſo fully occupieth both the bodie, and minde of the whole man, as he can haue ſmall leyſure for talke, or recreations.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>I knowe ſome that will iuſtly tell, how many acres e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery parcel of grounde conteineth onely by the viewe of them: not v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing either pole, or inſtrument.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Diuers ſurueyors by their great experience, and by the helpe of deedes, terrors, particulars. Iurors, and report of the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, can giue a great geſſe at the true contentes of landes: and thereupon will ſet downe their iudgementes, which maner of ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueying differeth from exactnes. He that is much exerciſed in the tals of mony can giue neereſt geſſe howe much bagges, and heapes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine vpon the viewe of them. Likewiſe they which are greatly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in buying of peeces of veluets, ſilkes, and cloths: can by their bulkes giue ſometimes neere geſſes at their contents: but yet their geſſes are vncertaine, and moſt commonly vntrue. The records of ſuch coniecturall ſurueyes, ought not to be produced as good, and ſufficient euidence for proofe of the quantitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>Is then a Mathematician the beſt ſurueyor, ought not any to be admitted vnto ſuruey but he?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>He that vnderſtandeth all the parts of ſuruey, beſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth to be admitted to that function. There be diuers Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticians that vnderſtand. Geometrie, Arithmetike, and Perſpectiue
<pb facs="tcp:20965:37"/> ſufficiently for the Mathematical part of ſurueie: that vnderſtand li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in the parts Legal, and Iudicial. Alſo there be diuers that vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the parts Legall, and Iudicial, that vnderſtand litle of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicals. Therefore when partitions, exchanges, buyings, and ſellings by the acre, are to be made, they to whom theſe matters ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine, if they will haue their buſineſſes exactly done: ſhould get ſuch a one as vnderſtandeth all the parts of ſurueie, or els two who by their knowledges ioyned together are able to make a perfect ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueie. If defection be in any of the three parts, the reſidue of the ſuruey is litle better then labour loſt, ſuch great errors will enſue thereof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>I would faine be acquainted with ſome that vnderſtand al the parts of ſurueie perfectly. You know many ſuch.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>I knowe verie fewe ſuch. Ye haue heard of M. Thomas Digges, he is verie ſkilful in all the three parts. All ſurueiors are greatly beholding vnto him, for ſetting forth three bookes of Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrie, in which hee learnedly teacheth Geometricall meaſurings. For the part mathematicall all good ſurueiors owe vnto him great reuerence, becauſe he is a lanthorne vnto them, aſwel in the ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the practiſe. He and M. Leonard Digges his father haue bin the firſt, and chiefeſt that haue giuen light, and taſt of this neceſſarie part of ſurueie in our vulgar tongue. M. Thomas Owen one of the Counſellours of the Citie of London (of any learned man towardes the Lawe) beſt vnderſtandeth al the parts of ſurueie as I haue heard from them that be ſkilful, and for ought that euer I could perceiue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. He wel vnderſtandeth diuers tongues, and is ſo wel furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of the beſt authors in diuers languages, that hee hath gotten much and rare knowledge from them. M. Iohn Hils an Auditor (of any man whoſe learning and practiſe I knowe) in my iudgement is the perfecteſt, and readieſt man in all the parts thereof. He vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth Arithmetike, Geometrie, and perſpectiue, both ſpeculatiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and practically ſingularly wel. His knowledge and daily exerciſe of Auditorie, mixt with the ſtudie of the common Lawes, &amp; his great ſearch and practiſe of the part Iudiciall, haue brought him to a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found iudgement and knowledge. M. Fardenando Malyn, and M. Iohn Malyn his brother can ſurueie ſingularly wel. They vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the Mathematical parts perfectly, and are of good ſtudie, and great practiſe in the other. M. Fardenando is the readieſt man in the field y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer I ſaw. M. Deuhurſt, M. Grent, &amp; M. Godfrey can ſurueie ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb facs="tcp:20965:38"/> well. M. Godfrey hath verie good knowledge in Perſpectiue. I aſſure my ſelfe that many others are verie ſkilful, and can do verie wel in al the parts thereof: but I can not report the ſkil of any vpon mine owne knowledge, ſauing of theſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>Me thinks many ſhould giue themſelues to be ſkilful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of ſurueie: and to vnderſtand the knowledge, and practiſe of al the parts thereof. What be the cauſes why there are ſo fewe ſuruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, that can ſufficiently ſurueie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Such ſufficient ſkil as a ſurueyor ſhould haue, before he ought to execute that office, can not bee attained but by a longer ſtudie, and a greater practiſe, then is commonly thought to bee had thereto. It is alſo one of the chargeableſt ſtudies, that one can enter into. There are fewe that wil take the paines to giue perfect inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to young beginners, &amp; to ſet them in the right courſe of ſtudy and practiſe, which is a great cauſe of much vaine expences. The Mathematical part ſéemeth ſo drie, and hard, at the firſt entraunce, that ſome (as wearied) giue ouer before they haue paſſed halfe way. Alſo meaſurers ignorant of Geometrie make quicker diſpatch, then the learned and ſkilful can: which ſo pleaſeth the ignorant becauſe it diminiſheth preſent charge, that they therefore litle regard him, that maketh true meaſure, which in troth is penie wiſedome, and pound fooliſhnes. Alſo through lack of good order in this weightie matter, braggers that by ſhowe of their inſtrument win credit, are ſooner reteyned by the ignorant then a ſufficient man. Some thinke that to be a great peece of cunning which in deede is eyther an error, or but a trifle. The benefite alſo to the ſkilful is ſo ſmall, and the charge to be in ſuch readineſſe as they ought ſo great, that they giue ouer as wearied, leauing the matter to ignorant diſpatchers, who ſticke not at any thing. If the learned and ſkilful, did vſe conferences, &amp; deuiſe waies, how theſe inconueniences might be redreſſed, true knowledge aduanced, and ignorance depreſſed, as the learned in other profeſſions do: great vtilitie would enſue vnto our commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weale therby. It is a lamentable thing that ſo great a miſchiefe (as the ignorance of true landmeaſuring bringeth) hath ſo long bin ſpied, and that no remedie is therefore prouided. Euerie man knoweth that lande is our riches in the hyeſt nature, and yet true ſurueying, and valuing thereof is ſhoufled vp, as though it were a matter of ſmall importance. If a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuer ſhould in ſtead of an hundreth pounds vſually receiue either
<pb facs="tcp:20965:38"/> too much or too litle, though it were vnder fourtie ſhillings, and the ouerſight but in monie, his Lord, if he knewe it, would thinke him verie vnſkilful and negligent in his office, and quickly haue an euill opinion of him therefore. But if ignorant meaſurers miſſe x. acres in an hunderth (whoſe value is commonly aboue fortie poundes) they are not euill thought of therefore, though it bee to the loſſe of ſo much inheritance. Ignoraunce beareth ſuch ſway, that for lack of good order theſe chances daily happen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter</speaker>
               <p>How may a man when he lacketh a good ſurueyor, knowe him that is ſufficient, from him that is inſufficient?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Rules can hardly be giuen vnto the ignorant of ſuruey, how to chooſe one that is ſufficient. If ſurueyors were in ſuch order (as by good reaſon they ſhould, the weightines of their charge conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered) then as the learned in other profeſſions are knowen from the vnlearned, ſo might they. Not any ſtudent of the Law can be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the bar, except by the benchers he be thought ſufficient. None can be admitted in the Vniuerſities to any degrees of learning but by the allowance of ancient graduates of the ſame profeſſion. If the ſkilful in the parts Mathematicall, Legal, and Iudicial would frind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſingly ioyne together to reforme, and inſtruct each others, and to reduce ſurueie to a perfect order: without doubt many which now vnderſtand but parts, and peeces rightly: but moe things erroniouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or lamely, would in ſhort ſpace proue ſufficient men. Alſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent good waies for the beſt inſtruction of young ſtudents thereof, would ſoon be had. They that enter themſelues into the ſtudie of this ſcience, and would perſeuere therein, are driuen to go ſo blindely and confuſedly to work, becauſe they know not where to haue right in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, that they fall into many errors, and receiue great diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohnſon</speaker>
               <p>Me thinks the number of ſurueyors in theſe daies is too great. Gentlemen know wel ynough how to let their lands to the vttermoſt. They haue cunning ynough for that matter, they néed no more help from ſkilfull men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Worſop</speaker>
               <p>Though ſome landlords deale ouer hardly with their te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, the fault thereof is not to be attributed to ſurueyors. Good &amp; ſkilfull ſurueyors will refourme thoſe enormities, and not augment them. The common people for the moſt part are in great feare when ſurueie is made of their land. If the ſurueie be ſkilfully made, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth
<pb facs="tcp:20965:39"/> ouer ſmall meaſures, and exceſſes of rents. None can ſo wel tel what is indifferent betwéene Lord, and tenant, as the ſkilful ſure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueyor. Some part of his charge conſiſteth vpon iudgement, therfore ſéeing he is in ſome reſpects a Iudge: if he be godly, &amp; iuſtly minded, he will not exact vpon the tenant, although the Lord pleaſe him for the ſurueie taking: but wil meaſure, and value, according to equitie and indifferencie, aſwell for the diſcharge of his conſcience, as the preſeruation of his credit. We are now come to the Townes end, we wil talke more of theſe matters an other time.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20965:39"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
